<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessed birth-day celebrated in some pious meditations, on the angels anthem. Luke 2. 14. Also holy raptures in contemplating of the most obserueable adjuncts about our Saviours nativitie. By Charles Fitz-Geffry.</title>
            <author>Fitz-Geffry, Charles, 1575?-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00814</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837916</idno>
  <idno type="VID">2263</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240864479</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 10935</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S102116</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99837916e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 798:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessed birth-day celebrated in some pious meditations, on the angels anthem. Luke 2. 14. Also holy raptures in contemplating of the most obserueable adjuncts about our Saviours nativitie. By Charles Fitz-Geffry.</title>
                  <author>Fitz-Geffry, Charles, 1575?-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield printer to the University, and are to be sold by Ed. Forrest,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>an. Dom. 1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christmas --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2263:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2263:1"/>
            <p>THE BLESSED BIRTH-DAY CELEBRATED <hi>IN</hi> Some Pious Meditations, on the ANGELS ANTHEM. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>ALSO HOLY RAPTVRES In contemplating of the most obserue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Adjuncts about our Saviours NATIVITIE.</p>
            <p>By CHARLES FITZ-GEFFRY.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Maxim. Taurinensis in Nat: Dom: h<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hodiè Christus natum est, nos renati.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD Printer to the University, and are to be sold by <hi>Ed. Forrest An. Dom.</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2263:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2263:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend Author on his severall workes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SIR, I not praise your witt, for that (all know)</l>
               <l>Praises it selfe: each line that thence doth flow</l>
               <l>Like to some pearle, or ray, or streame, well showes</l>
               <l>The Mine, Sunne, Fountaine, whence it first arose.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But that which ravishes iust praise from me,</l>
               <l>Is the choice method of your Poetrie;</l>
               <l>And that you could with such due equipage</l>
               <l>Sute seuerall poems to your severall age:</l>
               <l>So that in this your exemplary art</l>
               <l>Acts both the Poets, and the Preachers part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your younger wit, (as taking a delight</l>
               <l>In bold endeavours) ventur'd to recite</l>
               <l>The deeds of valiant Drake who by your skill,</l>
               <l>And strong descriptions, goes that voiage still</l>
               <l>Which once he did, and with full blasts of fame</l>
               <l>Yet sailes, (securely) round the earth againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, as experience taught you to survay</l>
               <l>The Worlds conditions, your free Muse would play</l>
               <l>In various Epigramms, where both for tongue,</l>
               <l>Conceit, and choise of verse, you seeme to runne</l>
               <l>With foremost Martiall, and so thriue therein;</l>
               <l>That you come nearest to the Goale next him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But having now retreated from the fome</l>
               <l>Of surging youth, and safe at length come home</l>
               <l>To quiet age, diviner thoughts inspire</l>
               <l>Your pregnant fancy, and with holier fire</l>
               <l>In flame you to the sweet discovery</l>
               <l>Of Heavenly mysteries: where the most high</l>
               <l>Must exercise your soaring braine, to tell</l>
               <l>The Natalls of our Saviour, which so well</l>
               <l>You haue perform'd with each nice circumstance</l>
               <l>Of time, and place, and persons, to advance</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2263:3"/>
               <l>Such lofty wonders, that you make to vs</l>
               <l>Those miracles seeme more miraculous.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is your praise: but will you heare me noise</l>
               <l>The shame of others that grow old in toies,</l>
               <l>Write plaies with spectacles, and spend an age</l>
               <l>Past threescore yeares on sonnets, and the stage:</l>
               <l>That chafe their palsied fancies, and molest</l>
               <l>With a forc't flame those embers that would rest:</l>
               <l>That bald, and dry, and sere, and wither'd, yet</l>
               <l>Yeild blossoms still, and chilblaines of their wit:</l>
               <l>As if (like Hesiod's infants) they still were</l>
               <l>But children at their almost hundreth yeare:</l>
               <l>That thinke their wild inventions too much pent</l>
               <l>In sacred taskes, and not their element</l>
               <l>To be in heavenly things, as if such stuff</l>
               <l>Were not conceited, rich, and fine enough</l>
               <l>For their loose numbers, or could not yeeld straines</l>
               <l>Of matter high enough to fill their veines</l>
               <l>With raptures; but o! how is this made vaine</l>
               <l>By noble Bartas! whose Heroicke braine</l>
               <l>Adorn'd Gods works, and like another light,</l>
               <l>Pictur'd the whole creation to our sight.</l>
               <l>Nay how is this made lye by those Saint-men,</l>
               <l>(Those spheares of witt) Tertullian, Nazianzen,</l>
               <l>Nissen, Lactantius, and more of that crue,</l>
               <l>That could be Fathers, and yet Poets too;</l>
               <l>And when they could not their rude enemies pierce</l>
               <l>With gentle prose, they batter'd them with verse,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But let them passe, and sucke the empty shout</l>
               <l>Of lewd applauses, which will shortly out</l>
               <l>In stench, and rottennesse, and then commit</l>
               <l>Their Authors to the <hi>Iudgement</hi> of their wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But surely who would dye (as they should doe)</l>
               <l>Good Poets, must first learne to be like you.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>HEN. BEESLEY A.A.A.M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2263:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> BLESSED BIRTH-DAY CELEBRATED IN SOME PIOUS MEDITATIONS, ON <hi>THE ANGELS ANTHEM.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE 2.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Glory to God in the highest, and on Earth Peace, Good will towards Men.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HY should not we with Ioy resound and sing</l>
               <l>The blessed Natals of our heauenly King?</l>
               <l>Why should not we with mirth salute the morne</l>
               <l>Of his Birth-day by whom we are new borne?</l>
               <l>See how each Creature in his kinde rejoyces,</l>
               <l>And shall not we lift vp melodious voyces?</l>
               <l>Harke how the Angels sing, shall we be sad?</l>
               <l>The greatest good is ours, be we most glad.</l>
               <l>Harke how the Star-enameld Heauens rebound</l>
               <l>With Eccho's of Angellike Anthems sound.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2263:4"/>
               <l>It is for Vs that they such ioyes expresse:</l>
               <l>And shall not we sing forth some thankfullnesse?</l>
               <l>Ioyne we in consort these sweet Quires among,</l>
               <l>In sundry voyces sing we all one song,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lasciuious songs, vaine Carols hence avaunt,</l>
               <l>And whatsoe're prophane throats vse to chaunt,</l>
               <l>Which through the Eares powre poison to the heart,</l>
               <l>A better subject doth this Day impart.</l>
               <l>To sacred songs is Sions Muse inclin'd:</l>
               <l>Some holy matter fits an holy mind.</l>
               <l>The King of Kings is subject of our verse,</l>
               <l>Whose praise all tongues are too few to rehearse.</l>
               <l>Sing we high myst'ries in an humble straine,</l>
               <l>And lofty matters in a lowly vaine.</l>
               <l>The sacred subiect (which we sing) affords</l>
               <l>Strong lines, but strong in matter not in words.</l>
               <l>For things so high they cannot be exprest</l>
               <l>By any words, the plainest are the best.</l>
               <l>He who was borne so humbly, doth refuse</l>
               <l>To haue his Birth sung by a swelling Muse.</l>
               <l>Ill doth a flaunting Phrase devotion fitt,</l>
               <l>We sing to shew our zeale, and not our witt.</l>
               <l>Let Gentils striue to be prophanely witty;</l>
               <l>This holy Day cals for an holy Ditty.</l>
               <l>Then let our Ditty answer to the Day,</l>
               <l>And with Heauens Quiristers let's sing and say,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O God, ô Man, ô God and Man in one,</l>
               <l>Th' eternall Fathers co-eternall Sonne;</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2263:4"/>
               <l>Who for Mans sake did'st Sonne of Man become,</l>
               <l>Disdaining not thine humble Handmaids wombe:</l>
               <l>Nor of thy Creature to be made did'st scorne,</l>
               <l>Ere time begotten, in times fulnesse borne:</l>
               <l>Who by thy Power did'st every day create,</l>
               <l>And by thy Birth did'st this day consecrate.</l>
               <l>O thou who<note n="a" place="margin">Revel. 22.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> art,</l>
               <l>Be th' <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of my heart!</l>
               <l>And while my Muse thy Birth-day doth rehearse,</l>
               <l>Be th' <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of my verse!</l>
               <l>Thou who so lowlie did'st descend to me,</l>
               <l>Mount vp my mind aloft, Lord, vnto thee!</l>
               <l>And from my foule errors dark fogs expell,</l>
               <l>Who doest in light inaccessible dwell:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.16</note>And let that neuer-erring star, thy word,</l>
               <l>Vnto thy Birth-place me conduct ô Lord!</l>
               <l>Shew me thy Cradle, let my soule behold</l>
               <l>The swathing cloathes that did thee once infold.</l>
               <l>Be thou the subject and the Author too</l>
               <l>Of what I muse, I say, I thinke, I doe:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vtinam praed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cando Verbum tuum aut lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dande nomen tuum tantum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>querer. Augustini.</note>O might my tongue b' imployed all my dayes</l>
               <l>Thy word to Preach, or to sing forth thy Praise!</l>
               <l>Thou who doest lend me matter, send me might,</l>
               <l>For none without thee can thee sing aright.</l>
               <l>And thou who art the word without beginning,</l>
               <l>Fit me with words, while I of thee am singing:</l>
               <l>My words with waight, and what I speak of thee</l>
               <l>(Who else am speechlesse) speak thou first in me:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Psal. 8.2.</note>Who out of sucklings mouthes doest strength ordaine,</l>
               <l>Loose thou the strings that doe my tongue restraine;</l>
               <l>And let that<note n="d" place="margin">Mark. 7.34.</note>
                  <hi>Ephphatha</hi> to me be spoken,</l>
               <l>Whereby the strings of stammering tongues are broken.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2263:5"/>
               <l>O tune my harsh voice to thine heauenly Kay,</l>
               <l>That for thy Birth with Angels sing I may,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Gen 3 16.</note>THE WOMANS SEED In <hi>Eden</hi> promised</l>
               <l>Is come to crush the cursed <hi>Serpents</hi> head;</l>
               <l>Whose comming all the Prophets haue foretold,</l>
               <l>The complement of Prophecies of old,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Col 1.19.</note>The fulnesse of the Figures true intent,</l>
               <l>The truth of what the <hi>Types</hi> did represent,</l>
               <l>The substance which the Ceremonies veil'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Reuel. 1.16.</note>
                  <hi>The Morning-star</hi> which seem'd to be conceal'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note>
                  <hi>Old Iacobs shilo,</hi> and the glorious <hi>Flowre</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Esay. 10.11.</note>
                  <hi>Of Iesses root.</hi> The Rod that did devour</l>
               <l>The Magick rods turn'd serpents. Euen he</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Iohn. 5.58.</note>Whose Day old <hi>Abraham</hi> desir'd to see.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Numb. 21.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 3.14.</note>The <hi>salving Serpent</hi> for their cure erected</l>
               <l>Who by th' infernall Serpent were infected:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Quicquid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st veteris Testamenti Christum so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat.</note>what euer in th' old Covenant is found,</l>
               <l>Did him whose comming now we sing resound:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 49.9.</note>
                  <hi>The Tribe of Iudahs Lyon,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Reuel. 5.5.</note>
                  <hi>who prevailes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T' vnclaspe the booke, &amp; loose the seauen shut seales,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All these are come to be by Vs possest,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 12.3.18.18.22.18. Act. 5.25. Gal. 3 8.</note>
                  <hi>who all generations maketh blest.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What others did expect, we doe enjoy:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Isai 9.6.</note>To vs that Sonne is borne, <hi>that blessed Boy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To vs is giuen which promised was to them,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ioy and glorie of Ierusalem:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall we not then with blessed Angels sing</l>
               <l>An holy Anthem to our heauenly King?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2263:5"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high</hi> who this hath wrought,</l>
               <l>And mans saluation thus about hath brought</l>
               <l>By wondrous wayes which none could doe, but One,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Psal. 77.14.72 18.</note>Who wondrous is in all his wayes alone.</l>
               <l>Well might his name be called<note n="r" place="margin">Isa. 9.6.</note>
                  <hi>Wonderfull,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whose Birth, Life, Death, whose rising were so full</l>
               <l>Of glorious wonders; and of wondrous glories;</l>
               <l>Such as the world nere found in all their stories.</l>
               <l>O with what wonders doe his Heauens abound,</l>
               <l>Sith sundry wonders in each worme is found!</l>
               <l>What thing so little is which he hath wrought,</l>
               <l>Which with a world of wonders is not fraught?</l>
               <l>And yet of all the wonders he hath done,</l>
               <l>Himselfe the greatest wonder is alone:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Mirabilis De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us in sanctis su<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>is. <hi>Psal 68. v. vlt.</hi>
                  </note>Wondrous in all his blessed Saints is he,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Si in sanctis suis mirabilis Deus, quomod non inseipso <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rabilis M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x. Taurin. ho. 1. in Nat. Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>Shall he not in himselfe more wondrous be?</l>
               <l>Who in his Baptists Birth was wondrous knowne,</l>
               <l>Shall he not be more wondrous in his owne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O sacred Riddles which no ingenie</l>
               <l>Or Art of man or Angels can vntie!</l>
               <l>Which who so ere would haue to be disclos'd</l>
               <l>Must with his Heyfer plough who them compos'd,</l>
               <l>And being once disclos'd who can refraine</l>
               <l>His tongue from tuning this Angellike straine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Magn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>{que} ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> paren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Progenies Sannaz. de part virg. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>Behold a Sonne as ancient as his Father</l>
               <l>Being without beginning both together.</l>
               <l>Twixt whom and him this difference is alone,</l>
               <l>That he the Father is, and this the Sonne.</l>
               <l>The one begets, the other is begot,</l>
               <l>Yet th' one in time from th' other differs not.</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2263:6"/>
               <l>For both a Co-eternall being had,<note place="margin">Christ the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ernall Sonne of God and God equall with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Ere time or any Creature else was made.</l>
               <l>God alway was a Father, and was neuer</l>
               <l>Whithout his Sonne who with him was for euer.</l>
               <l>So, of himselfe the glorious Eye of heauen</l>
               <l>Begets a Beame, which with himselfe is euen</l>
               <l>In time, in being: For the Beame begun</l>
               <l>In the same instant with his sire the Sunne.</l>
               <l>So from the spring a springing streame doth flow,</l>
               <l>Which in it is, and yet doth from it goe:</l>
               <l>So yeelds the Incense a sweet smell, and this</l>
               <l>Both of and with and in the Incense is.</l>
               <l>So doth the pregnant minde a word beget,</l>
               <l>Twixt whom and it Time doth no distance set.</l>
               <l>The Sun, the spring, the Incense, the minde afford</l>
               <l>At once the beame, the streame, the Smel, the word.</l>
               <l>Cannot the Father doe that in his Sonne,</l>
               <l>Which in the Creature we see daily done?</l>
               <l>What they by him in time performe, could he</l>
               <l>Not in himselfe doe from Eternitie?</l>
               <l>But this eternall Son-ship scorns compare,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Esay. 53.8.</note>
                  <hi>Who can his generation declare?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Before thou canst thy makers ofspring show,</l>
               <l>Presumptuous man, first learn thine owne to know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Peace<note n="†" place="margin">Arrius who said that there was a time when the Son was not.</note> damned Heretike, blaspheme no more,</l>
               <l>Say not, the <hi>Father</hi> was in time before</l>
               <l>The Sonne: and that there was a time wherein</l>
               <l>The Sonne was not, who did in time begin</l>
               <l>To be: For here is no prioritie</l>
               <l>In time, in Deitie, in dignitie.</l>
               <l>No time before the Father euer was,</l>
               <l>No time before the Sonne could euer passe.</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2263:6"/>
               <l>What threed of time before him could be spinning,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Iohn. 1.1. In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was the word.</note>Who is the word which was ere times beginning?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">And that word was with God.</note>That word which euer was with God:<note n="y" place="margin">And that word was God.</note> That word</l>
               <l>which euer was, is, shall be God the Lord:</l>
               <l>What time could be before him, who did frame</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">All things were made by him.</note>Both time, and all that man can Creature name?</l>
               <l>Same God, same Essence, same Eternitie,</l>
               <l>And all the same seeme Personalitie.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Non quia qui summus Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter est &amp; Fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us hic est, Sed quia quod sūmu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pater est &amp; Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius hoc est. Sedulius.</note>The Sonne we say, and doe not say amisse,</l>
               <l>The same, not who, but what the Father is.</l>
               <l>Same, not the same, the Father and the Sonne,</l>
               <l>Not same in person are in substance one.</l>
               <l>One, yet not one. Father, and Sonne (we say)</l>
               <l>One God indeed, but not one person they.</l>
               <l>The Sonne of God both Sonne and God must be,</l>
               <l>God of himselfe, Sonne of his Father He:</l>
               <l>So nor the father is the Sonne, nor yet</l>
               <l>The Sonne the Father, who did him beget.</l>
               <l>But both the Father, and the Sonne, the word,</l>
               <l>One God we doe acknowledge and one Lord.</l>
               <l>What time, what distance could then be betweene</l>
               <l>Who both are one and euer so hath beene?</l>
               <l>If God had once no Sonne, then once must he,</l>
               <l>Without <seg rend="sup">z</seg> the <hi>brightnesse</hi> of his glorie be.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 13.</note>If he be God o're all, blessed for euer,</l>
               <l>What time could then him from his Father seuer?<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note>
               </l>
               <l>If that the word in time from God did come,</l>
               <l>There was a time, when God himselfe was dumbe:</l>
               <l>If God did his<note n="c" place="margin">Esai. 53.1. where by the arme of the Lord the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers some of them doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand Christ.</note>
                  <hi>Arme</hi> in time attaine,</l>
               <l>A time there was when God did maim'd remaine.</l>
               <l>So must they say of God, and so blaspheme,</l>
               <l>Who of a time before the Sonne doe dreame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2263:7"/>
               <l>Shew then the time proud Heretike, wherein</l>
               <l>He was not, who for euer God hath beene.</l>
               <l>Shew when the Sonne was not, who, though the Sonne</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Isa. 9.6.</note>Yet <hi>th' euerlasting Fathers</hi> name hath wonne.</l>
               <l>Shew when he did begin to be, who seeing</l>
               <l>He is God, with God had euerlasting being.</l>
               <l>Assigne a time beyond Eternitie:</l>
               <l>If not, recant thy cursed Heresie.</l>
               <l>Consid'ring such a wondrous glorious birth,</l>
               <l>Shall we not say, and sing with heauenly Myrth,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on earth be peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The humane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ature of Christ as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s the sonne of the Virgin.</note>Behold a Sonne who Father hath and mother,</l>
               <l>Yet may be said, to haue nor one nor other.</l>
               <l>In heauen a Father without mother knowne,</l>
               <l>A Mother here he had but Father none.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 7.3.</note>The true <hi>Melchizedec</hi> from heauen descending,</l>
               <l>Who nor beginning hath of dayes nor ending:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Reuel. 22.3.</note>The first, the last: King, Priest and Prophet true,</l>
               <l>To teach, to sacrifice and to subdue.</l>
               <l>Who only worthy was to haue none other,</l>
               <l>Father then God, nor then a Virgin Mother,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Reasons why the Messias was to be borne of a pure Virgine.</note>For twas not comely that one Sonne should know</l>
               <l>Two Fathers; one aboue, one here below.</l>
               <l>And how could he man without sinne be made</l>
               <l>If to his Father he some sinner had?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Iohn. 3.6.</note>That which <hi>is borne of flesh</hi> flesh needes must be,</l>
               <l>And how could sinfull flesh from sinne flesh free?</l>
               <l>Had any <hi>Adams</hi> sonne his Father bin,</l>
               <l>He had receau'd with <hi>Adams</hi> seed his sinne.</l>
               <l>And had he ought of <hi>Adams</hi> sinne possessed,</l>
               <l>Then how could <hi>Adams</hi> seed in him be blessed?</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2263:7"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Th' high Priest</hi> by whom we should be reconcil'd</l>
               <l>Must holy, harmelesse be, and vndefil'd,</l>
               <l>Sep'rate from sinners (though<note n="i" place="margin">Isai. 53.13</note> mong them reputed)</l>
               <l>For had he beene himselfe with sinne polluted</l>
               <l>How could he from vs our pollutions take!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He must be pure who others pure shall make.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">De imm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> conceptum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mine nullu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cere mundu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> potest nisi i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> per semet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mundus est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gregor. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in Iob.</note>Who could them clense. who were of sinfull seed</l>
               <l>Conceau'd, saue he who did no clensing need?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Quis eni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> peccata m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> tolleret, nisi quem pecca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non cadit?</note>Who can the worlds sinne take away, but He</l>
               <l>Who from all spot and blot of sinne is free?</l>
               <l>The beame out of mine eye he plucks alone,</l>
               <l>Who hath nor beame nor blemish in his owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus did the heauenly Providence dispose</l>
               <l>That euen his Birth should what he is disclose:</l>
               <l>True Man, because of Woman borne, but not</l>
               <l>Meere Man, because no Father him begot.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Secundu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conditionem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turae natus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> faemina, sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> conditionem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curae natus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Virgine T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> as Part <hi>3.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Quaest. <hi>31.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tic. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note>Thus by his naturall Birth true man we know him,</l>
               <l>His supernaturall more then man doth shew him.</l>
               <l>And thus the heauenly wisedome did ordaine,</l>
               <l>That they who by a<note n="†" place="margin">It is prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> that Eue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Virgine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> when she<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> transgress<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Polanus</note> Virgins sinne were slaine,</l>
               <l>Should by a Virgins seed be sau'd:<note n="*" place="margin">Vt vnde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> dedit paena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> etas daret <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> salutem. Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lius</note> And whence</l>
               <l>Sin came, God would saluation draw from thence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let all the world shew such a sonne againe</l>
               <l>Whose Birth so many wonders doth containe.</l>
               <l>A Lambe new falne, <seg rend="sup">i</seg> slaine ere the world begun,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Mothers Father, and his Daughters Sonne:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Doue</hi> hatcht in the nest himselfe did build:</l>
               <l>A flowre in winter sprung that fram'd the field</l>
               <l>From whence it sprung.<note n="k" place="margin">Reuel. 7</note>
                  <hi>A Lillie risen new</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That made the bed and garden where it grew.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 2.</note>A stone cut without hands which with one dash</l>
               <l>The Iron, Clay, Brasse, Siluer, Gold did quash</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2263:8"/>
               <l>Of which that dreadfull Image was compos'd</l>
               <l>Which to the great<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34: Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ezzar.</note>
                  <hi>Caldean</hi> was disclos'd.</l>
               <l>In visions of the night.<note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 118.22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. 21.47. Act. 4.11.</note>
                  <hi>The corner stone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That built, and beares the Fabrick built thereon:</l>
               <l>Who though the foolish builders him rejected,</l>
               <l>Now in the Corner is chiefe stone erected.</l>
               <l>Let all the world now shew vs such a Child</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Adams</hi> seed, not with his sinne defil'd.</l>
               <l>A Child who nere by man begotten was,</l>
               <l>Who doth his Mother farre in age surpasse,</l>
               <l>And match his Father in antiquitie,</l>
               <l>Elder then th' eldest of his Pedigree.</l>
               <l>A Child who made all Children and the Place</l>
               <l>And Time wherein and when himselfe borne was.</l>
               <l>A Child that's God, and<note n="*" place="margin">Isai. 63.1.</note> God mighty to saue,</l>
               <l>All those<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 17.12.</note> whom vnto him his Father gaue.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 7.4.</note>
                  <hi>Th' ancient of dayes</hi> borne in an houre: The light</l>
               <l>Of both the Worlds arising in the night.</l>
               <l>A Child who had he not to Vs beene borne,</l>
               <l>All generations had beene quite forelorne.</l>
               <l>Should not the strangest Child who came to saue</l>
               <l>The world, the strangest Mother likewise haue?</l>
               <l>And so he had: We truely may averre,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No Sonne like him, no Mother like to her.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Nec primam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> visa est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abere secū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am. Bern. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gil. Nat. ser. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>For such a Mother neuer was before,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And such another neuer shall be more.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let all the world now shew vs such a Mother,</l>
               <l>And say which is more wondrous one or other.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She for a Mother, or he for a Sonne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It must be say'd, when all is say'd and done,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O wondrous Mother, but more wondrous Sonne.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2263:8"/>
               <l>For such a saving Sonne, both Mother may</l>
               <l>With Angels sing, and we with them may say</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Behold a Mother, yet a Virgin still,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Mariam no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> libido impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitsed fides.</note>Whose Wombe not lust, but liuely Faith did fill:</l>
               <l>Before, and in, and after Birth a Mayd,</l>
               <l>Of whom 'mong all her sex it may be said.</l>
               <l>Sh' enioy'd by bringing forth that heauenly Boy,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gaudia Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris habens cum Virginitatis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore. Bern.</note>A Virgins honour, with a Mothers joy:</l>
               <l>Behold a field which nere by man was tild,</l>
               <l>Wheat whence is made, the bread of life doth yeild.</l>
               <l>Thus ere the Heauens<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 2.5.6.</note> did showers on Earth distill,</l>
               <l>Amy'st her pregnant wombe with fruit did fill.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Iudg. 6.37.38.</note>Thus <hi>Gedeons fleece</hi> was moist when all was drie,</l>
               <l>And dry when all about it moist did lie.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Exod. 3.2.</note>Thus <hi>Moses bush</hi> sent forth a flaming fume,</l>
               <l>And burning did not with the fire consume.</l>
               <l>Thus did Faiths fire the Virgins heart inflame,</l>
               <l>And yet abolisht not her Virgin-name:</l>
               <l>Her swelling bellie nothing did abate</l>
               <l>The entirenesse of her Maydenhead, state.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Numb. 17.8.</note>And thus on <hi>Aarons Rod ripe Almonds grew,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not set in earth nor moist'ned with the dew.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Vt virga <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uit absque ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, sic Virgo concepit non ex homine Bern. Sup Missus est hom. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>And thus from <hi>Maries</hi> Wombe<note n="x" place="margin">Isai. 53.2.</note> a Plant proceeded,</l>
               <l>Which neither setting, neither plantage needed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neuer till now two <hi>Phoenixes</hi> were seene</l>
               <l>At once; For this the vsuall course hath beene</l>
               <l>(If all be true, that Naturallists haue told,)</l>
               <l>The young ones birth brings death vnto the old:</l>
               <l>One <hi>Phoenix</hi> here another forth doth bring,</l>
               <l>And yet her selfe is sau'd from perishing:</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2263:9"/>
               <l>The Mother there dies to produce an other,</l>
               <l>But here the Child must die to saue the Mother,</l>
               <l>The young one must himselfe of life depriue,</l>
               <l>Or else the Mother <hi>Phoenix</hi> cannot liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thou ô man doest aske how this may be,</l>
               <l>The same that answer'd her must answer thee.</l>
               <l>When of the Messenger she did demand</l>
               <l>How this with possibility might stand.</l>
               <l>That she should haue a Man-child of her owne,</l>
               <l>Who neuer Man in all her life had knowne?</l>
               <l>All things are possible with God, whose skill</l>
               <l>And power to worke are equall with his will.</l>
               <l>Least we should doubt of this he first would doe</l>
               <l>Things all as strange as this, and stranger too.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nnon putas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m novum pue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n̄ in aluo Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nis potuisse for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are qui quum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rimum conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et heminē, nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iscera materna <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae fiuit? Max. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. <hi>3.</hi> de Nat.</note>He who at first to frame a Man did need</l>
               <l>Neither a Mothers wombe nor Fathers seed,</l>
               <l>Could he not now forme in a Virgins Womb</l>
               <l>A Child, who from no Fathers seed should come?</l>
               <l>Could not the same who first made man of Earth</l>
               <l>Procure a Mayden to bring forth a Birth?</l>
               <l>He, who a Woman of a Man could frame</l>
               <l>Without a Womans help, could not the same</l>
               <l>A perfect Man now of a Woman make,</l>
               <l>One who no man should for his Father take?</l>
               <l>Let this suffice:<note n="*" place="margin">Ratio facti est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otentia fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iētis; Considera au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorum &amp; telle dubitationem. Tertullian de resurrect Carnis.</note> The reason of the deed,</l>
               <l>Doth from the doers will and powre proceed.</l>
               <l>Consider who it is that wrought the fact,</l>
               <l>Once know the Author, doubt not of the Act.</l>
               <l>But for the Act the Author magnifie,</l>
               <l>Ioyning with th' Angels in their melodie,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2263:9"/>
               <l>Astronomers of the <hi>Zodiac</hi> cease to talke,</l>
               <l>And the twelue signes through which the Sun doth walke</l>
               <l>Say what you will you cannot well avow,</l>
               <l>The Sun in <hi>Virgo</hi> truely was till now.</l>
               <l>You neuer did vntill this day espie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heauen low as Earth, and Earth as Heauen made high.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In all your houses such a match was neuer,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heauen comes and woes and weddeth Earth for euer.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You neuer saw what now you see is done,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Pregnant Moone, a Sublunary Sunne.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You neuer saw that light which shines so farre,</l>
               <l>Veil'd in a Stall, revealed by a Starre.</l>
               <l>Alter the Motto in your <hi>Almanakes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For now your anciently-said saw mistakes.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Sapiens domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabitur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>stris</note>
                  <hi>A wiseman ruler ore the Stars shall be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The wisemen now rul'd by a Starre we see:</l>
               <l>Who from the rising of the Sunne are prest</l>
               <l>To see the Sunne arising in the West.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come noble<note n="*" place="margin">The wise mē held two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siās. The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians of old worshipped the Sunne.</note>
                  <hi>Persians</hi> now learne to adore</l>
               <l>A greater Sunne, then that you did before:</l>
               <l>A Sunne which th' other made, and to him lends</l>
               <l>That light which he vnto the world extends.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Iosh. 10.12.</note>A Sunne which once commanded yours to stay</l>
               <l>His restlesse race, and to produce the day.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Isai. 38.8.</note>And at another time enforc'd his shade</l>
               <l>To turne full ten degrees quite retrograde:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 23.44.45.</note>And who shall shortly so ecclips his light,</l>
               <l>That all the world at noone shall put on night.</l>
               <l>When Earths vast globe in sable darknesse shall</l>
               <l>Attend as Mourners at his Funerall:</l>
               <l>Then shall the learned<note n="†" place="margin">Dionysius are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opagita, cuius illa vox celebra tur, aut Deus naturae patitur aut mundi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>china dissolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note>
                  <hi>Areopagite</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Crie out, amazed at the vncouth sight,</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2263:10"/>
               <l>Either the God of Natures suffers wrong,</l>
               <l>Or the worlds frame shall be dissolu'd ere long.</l>
               <l>Boue all your Stars adore this rising Sun,</l>
               <l>And if the Spheres make musicke as they run,</l>
               <l>Be sure no better straine then this can be</l>
               <l>The sweet Faburthen to their Melodie,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Behold the <hi>Lambe</hi> of God, the <hi>Lambe</hi> and God,</l>
               <l>Who maketh those things euen which earst were odd.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The substāce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the soule, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Bodie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he diuine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ubstance.</note>
                  <hi>Three Substances, two Natures, Person one,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The sacred Godhead chiefe expression.</l>
               <l>As in the euer blessed <hi>Trinitie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>One holy Nature is in Persons three,</l>
               <l>So in one Sonne who flesh for vs did take,</l>
               <l>Two Natures, Gods and ours, one Person make.</l>
               <l>Three Persons there one substance doe possesse,</l>
               <l>One Person here enioies three substances.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O blessed bloud! O sacred Vnion,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all Vnion.</note>That joineth three in two, and two in one!</l>
               <l>Three substances in Natures two agree,</l>
               <l>These two in one, This One, one, two, and three.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vnio Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alis sed non: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er sonarum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nio natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um sed non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aturalis quiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pernaturalis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ommunicatie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>diomatum.</note>By vertue of an Vnion Personall,</l>
               <l>But not of Persons: Neither naturall,</l>
               <l>Although of Natures, but substantiall</l>
               <l>Because of substances, vnited so</l>
               <l>That neither their owne properties foregoe:</l>
               <l>But such a freindlie enterchange they make,</l>
               <l>That each with other doth in speech partake,</l>
               <l>And what is said of God, the same of man</l>
               <l>(Sith God and man are one) affirme we can:</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2263:10"/>
               <l>And what of man said properly may be,</l>
               <l>The same likewise of God affirme may we.</l>
               <l>Thus doe we say (and what we say is true)</l>
               <l>That God did die and man did death subdue.</l>
               <l>God died, because the Person who did die</l>
               <l>Was not meere man, but God eternallie:</l>
               <l>And man subdued death, because the same</l>
               <l>Christ God and man both died and ouercame.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Act 20.28.</note>So by his bloud a Church God purchased</l>
               <l>Vnto himselfe: what bloud hath God to shed?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.8.</note>So was the Lord of glory Crucifide,</l>
               <l>When Christ the Lord of glory for vs dy'de.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Mark. 9.6.</note>So sins of men the Sonne of man forgiues,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Mark. 2.11.</note>Which who can doe, saue God who sin-lesse liues.</l>
               <l>These speeches in the <hi>Abstract</hi> disagree,</l>
               <l>In sense compounded well accorded be.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord what is man that only for his sake</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' Almighty should such strange exchanges make?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Videatur D. Bernard In vigil. Nat. Ser. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>What higher is then God, then Earth more base?</l>
               <l>Yet so farre God vouchsafeth Earth to grace,</l>
               <l>So humbly God doth vnto Earth descend,</l>
               <l>So largelie God doth cause Earth to extend,</l>
               <l>So neerly God, Earth to himselfe vniteth,</l>
               <l>So firme a league t'wixt him and it he plighteth</l>
               <l>That what God doth that Earth is said to doe,</l>
               <l>And what Earth suffers God doth suffer too.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">aduerte o homo quia limus es &amp; ne sis superbus, quia Deo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctus es, &amp; ne sis ingratus. Bern. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i supr.</note>Man know thou art but earth, Pride therefore hate:</l>
               <l>Man, thou art join'd to God, be not ingrate:</l>
               <l>But sing to him by whom advanc'd thou art</l>
               <l>With lofty voice but with an humble Heart,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2263:11"/>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Christ his great humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming man.</note>
                  <hi>Lord what is man that only for his sake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' Almighty should such strange exchanges make?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Eternity an Infant is become,</l>
               <l>The strength of Israel weak, that word is dumb.</l>
               <l>He whom the Heauen of Heauens cannot containe</l>
               <l>In narrow bowels doth impent remaine:</l>
               <l>Borne is he in a base vnworthy stall,</l>
               <l>Who vs advanceth to Heauens glorious Hall:</l>
               <l>He who doth all things fit, fits not a Crach,</l>
               <l>Heauen vnto Earth, God vnto man doth match.</l>
               <l>He who doth sillie man like Angels make</l>
               <l>An homely lodging with poore Beasts doth take:</l>
               <l>The worlds Creator and Commaunder great</l>
               <l>An Inne for loue or mony cannot get,</l>
               <l>But from fit lodging they doe him expell,</l>
               <l>Who with a word can lodge them all in hell.</l>
               <l>He cries to whom all hearts for help doe call,</l>
               <l>He cannot help himselfe who helpeth all.</l>
               <l>Euen He from whom th' Angels their knowledge learn,</l>
               <l>His right hand from his left cannot discerne:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note>who all things by his word vpholds, euen he</l>
               <l>By Womans feeble hand vpheld must be</l>
               <l>For feare of falling. And th' Almighty one</l>
               <l>Without his Creature cannot stand alone.</l>
               <l>The Way as yet the way to none can shew,</l>
               <l>The Truth not yet can truth from falshood know.</l>
               <l>Th' Immortall putteth on Mortalitie</l>
               <l>The euerlasting Life begins to die,</l>
               <l>That by his Birth he may that debt defray,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which Man did owe, but none saue God could pay.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The souls Physitian is to Death giuen ouer,</l>
               <l>That so the Sin-sick Patient may recouer.</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2263:11"/>
               <l>A desp'rate cure for desp'rate maladie:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The head must off or the whole body die.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who is mans head but God? But ö! How can</l>
               <l>God die? God may, if he become a Man.</l>
               <l>God is become a man subject to death,</l>
               <l>A subject which the Conquerour conquereth.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note>
                  <hi>Because the Children were of flesh compos'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Christ ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lasting Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Isai. 9.6. Heb. 2.26.</note>
                  <hi>Their Father would be in that flesh inclos'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That so by Death he might o'recome that euill,</l>
               <l>Which had the power of Death, that is the Diuell.</l>
               <l>The Angels Nature he refus'd to take,</l>
               <l>But man of <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed himselfe would make.</l>
               <l>That in our Nature he might him subdue,</l>
               <l>Who first our feeble Nature ouerthrew:</l>
               <l>That man on Sathan might avenge mans wrong,</l>
               <l>And them redeeme whom he held Captiue long:<note place="margin">Christ by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> humiliation loseth nothi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of his Glory</note>
               </l>
               <l>For greater is the glory and the merit,</l>
               <l>When feeble flesh o'recomes a potent spirit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God is become a Man. The ioyful'st newes</l>
               <l>That euer was or shal be: Yet ensues</l>
               <l>No alteration neither diminution,</l>
               <l>No losse, no mixture here, much lesse confusion.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Ille mā<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> semper erat, quod non era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> esse Incipiens Prudentius P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chomach.</note>Becomming what he was not, he remaines</l>
               <l>That which he euer was. The manhood gaines,</l>
               <l>The Godhead looseth not.<note n="*" place="margin">mihi contul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; sibi mansi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Prudentius i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> To me he giues</l>
               <l>Himselfe, and yet his owne he euer liues.</l>
               <l>That which he was he is, yet once was not</l>
               <l>That which he is. A Nature he hath got</l>
               <l>More then he had, and yet he still retaines</l>
               <l>That which he had.<note n="†" place="margin">Hinc illud crum Aenig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Sum quod er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> nec eram quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> sum nunc, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cor vtrumq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ignoras nisi me parts ab tra{que} tenes.</note> And having both, remaines</l>
               <l>But one: And though he take one Nature more,</l>
               <l>Yet is he but one Person as before.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2263:12"/>
               <l>God he was still, not Man vntill this tide,</l>
               <l>Hence forth both God and Man he doth abide:</l>
               <l>A time there was when man he was not showne,</l>
               <l>But when he was not God no time was knowne.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ante vllum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pus Deus in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Christus. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erbum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pe caro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>itit esse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d fuerat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bum carnis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> glutinat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> vbi supr.</note>
                  <hi>God before time, and in times fulnesse Christ,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Remaineth still the greatest and the high'st.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on alter ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, alter ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tre, sed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r ex patre, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er ex ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eucherius. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>2.</hi> de Nat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> homo sic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us es vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fis alter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> alter.</note>
                  <hi>The word made Flesh, the word remaineth still,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor is it emptied though the Flesh it fill.</l>
               <l>Nor doth he of his highnesse ought abate,</l>
               <l>Though humbly he descend to our estate:</l>
               <l>But stooping to advance vs who before</l>
               <l>Were low, himselfe is nothing yet the lower.</l>
               <l>And though for Man made Sonne of Man he be,</l>
               <l>Yet still the Sonne of God remaineth he.</l>
               <l>The Godhead so the Manhood doth possesse,</l>
               <l>That for the Man God nothing is the lesse.</l>
               <l>A lower state of Son-ship he doth choose,</l>
               <l>And yet his former Son-ship doth not loose.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>osper de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouident. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>risto est <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ud &amp; ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, non alius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> alias. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us.</note>And thus two sundry wayes he is a Sonne,</l>
               <l>As God, as Man, yet not two Sonnes but one.</l>
               <l>One way the Sonne of God, Sonne of his Mother</l>
               <l>Another way: Both wayes one, not another.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Venit in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>undum, non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>posita sed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>posita ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>state. As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mpta est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umanitas, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on consump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> diuinitas:-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucherius v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i supr.</note>His glory not cast off but lay'd aside,</l>
               <l>To Earth he come, yet doth in Heauen abide.</l>
               <l>Euen so some Prince or Lord of great repute,</l>
               <l>Leaues off his owne, puts on a Servants sute,</l>
               <l>Who though a servile habite him invest,</l>
               <l>Yet is not of his honour dispossest.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That golden Eye which gilds the world with day,</l>
               <l>Reaching to Earth yet still in Heauen doth stay:</l>
               <l>So doth the Sonne of God to Vs arriue</l>
               <l>On Earth, and yet with God in Heauen doth liue.</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2263:12"/>
               <l>And as my speech arriveth vnto thee,</l>
               <l>Whose Eare receaues it, yet remaines with me:</l>
               <l>So did the Fathers Word to me attaine,</l>
               <l>And with the Father vnremou'd remaine.</l>
               <l>Or as mine Arme extended doth abide,</l>
               <l>With ioynts and sinnews to my shoulder tide:</l>
               <l>So reacht the Lord his<note n="h" place="margin">Isai. 53.1. Vid. Supr. Pag.</note> Arme to me in loue,</l>
               <l>Yet from himselfe he did it not remoue.</l>
               <l>What honour should we yeeld to him who thus,</l>
               <l>Was pleas'd t' embase himselfe to honour vs?</l>
               <l>Can we doe lesse then in our best tun'd layes</l>
               <l>With blessed Angels sing vnto his praise?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Greatnesse little to become was pleas'd,</l>
               <l>Yet to continue Great he neuer ceas'd:</l>
               <l>Thus Heauens high King swath'd in a Cratch doth lie,</l>
               <l>Yet looseth nothing of his Majestie.</l>
               <l>He who the glorious Angels did create,</l>
               <l>Becomes a<note n="i" place="margin">Psal. 22.6.</note> Worme yet keeps his owne estate.</l>
               <l>God had his lowlinesse enough commended,</l>
               <l>Had he but to an Angels state descended.</l>
               <l>For twixt an Angel and a Worme, more ods</l>
               <l>Is not, then twixt an Angels state and Gods.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Nihil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuisset subli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitas nisi ad fuisset humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas Heinsiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hom. in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan.</note>Had he not dain'd himselfe to humble thus,</l>
               <l>What good had all his greatnesse done to Vs?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Christ his humiliation should teach vs humilitie.</note>Great cause haue we t' embrace humility,</l>
               <l>Sith God himselfe embraced vs thereby.</l>
               <l>When Greatnesse vengeance for our sinns did craue,</l>
               <l>Humilitie it was that did vs saue.</l>
               <l>When Majestie and Iustice 'gainst vs stood,</l>
               <l>Then Mercy sought, Humilitie wrought our good.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2263:13"/>
               <l>When we to Hell were falne, then God did daine</l>
               <l>To stoope to Earth to raise vs vp againe.</l>
               <l>Neuer had man from Earth to Heauen attain'd,</l>
               <l>Had God to stoop to Earth from Heauen disdain'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vide ô homo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uid pro te actus est De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>: Doctrinam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umilitatis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnosce nondū <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oquente Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tore. August. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le Temp. ser. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>Learne of thy Lord, proud man, humble to be,</l>
               <l>Who read this humble Lecture vnto thee.</l>
               <l>Ere he could read or speake: His Incarnation</l>
               <l>Was his first Lecture of Humiliation.</l>
               <l>When being God he stooped to be Man,</l>
               <l>Whence greater Glory at the last he wan:</l>
               <l>When as his Father did him so advance,</l>
               <l>And so his name aboue all names enhance.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note>That at the name of Iesus every knee</l>
               <l>In Heauen, on Earth, in Hell should bended be.</l>
               <l>What can man loose by his Humility,</l>
               <l>Sith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od himselfe advanced was thereby?</l>
               <l>That meeknesse which at first his Birth did preach</l>
               <l>His words, his deeds throughout his Life did teach.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 11.21. The commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie with exhortation therevnto.</note>Learne yee of Me (saith He) for I am meeke:</l>
               <l>What better thing then Learning can we seeke?</l>
               <l>Then Christ, what better teacher can there be?</l>
               <l>What better lesson then Humilitie?</l>
               <l>Who would not, that can good from ill discerne,</l>
               <l>Of the best Teacher the best lesson learne!</l>
               <l>By the same Paces we to God must tend,</l>
               <l>By which his Sonne did vnto Vs descend.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 21.5.</note>
                  <hi>Behold thy King comes meeke to thee,</hi> wilt thou</l>
               <l>Come proud vnto thy King? will he allow</l>
               <l>In thee who art with mortall Clay invested,</l>
               <l>What in his glorious Angels he detested?</l>
               <l>Pride them from Heauen and glory did eject,</l>
               <l>Humilitie to Heauen must vs erect.</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2263:13"/>
               <l>With God, who highnesse is it selfe, more high</l>
               <l>Nothing is held then low Humilitie.</l>
               <l>† In Gods esteeme much rather is allow'd,<note n="*" place="margin">Melior est peccator hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis quàm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ustus super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Augustin de Temp: Ser. <hi>44.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An humble sinner then a iust man proud.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is not God high? yet he who will attaine</l>
               <l>Vnto his highnesse, lowly must remaine.</l>
               <l>Erect thy selfe, he doth from thee retire:</l>
               <l>Deject thy selfe, thou doest to him aspire.</l>
               <l>For when he sees thy stooping to deject thee,</l>
               <l>Himselfe stoopes downe more highly to erect thee.</l>
               <l>The Proud a farre off he beholds to scorne them,</l>
               <l>The Humble he regards with grace t' adorne them.</l>
               <l>Sweet Sauiour by thy lowlinesse thou showest,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The best Ambition is who shall be lowest.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What more becomes a Christian, then the same</l>
               <l>To be to Christ, which Christ for him became?</l>
               <l>What griues the blessed Spirits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o seek our blisse,</l>
               <l>What more doth glad the Fiends our foes, then this</l>
               <l>To see a lowly God, a lof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Man,</l>
               <l>An humble Christ, and a proud Christian?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus God is one become ô man, with thee,</l>
               <l>That thou againe at one with God might'st be.</l>
               <l>Thus is th' <hi>Abyssus</hi> fild, the <hi>Chasma</hi> clos'd,</l>
               <l>Which twixt our God and Vs sinne interpos'd.</l>
               <l>This he<note n="n" place="margin">Col. 1.9.</note>
                  <hi>in whom all fulnesse dwels,</hi> hath done,</l>
               <l>Who being both himselfe<note n="o" place="margin">Ephes. 2.14.</note>
                  <hi>hath made both one.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We could not come to him, to vs he came,</l>
               <l>Euen what we are that he himselfe became;</l>
               <l>Saue only sinne, which he came to abolish,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Ephes. Vt supr.</note>And that <hi>partition-wall</hi> quite to demolish,</l>
               <l>Which severed God and Vs. Now ioyne we may,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Man vnto God by man hath found away.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2263:14"/>
               <l>The Patient could not to the Physitian goe,</l>
               <l>The kind Physitian comes to him: And so</l>
               <l>Vpon himselfe he our disease deriues,</l>
               <l>That from himselfe and vs both he it driues.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord what is man, that only for his sake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' Almighty should such strange exchanges make?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Th' Angels themselues such loue considering,</l>
               <l>In ioyfull admiration doe sing,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Once God of <hi>Adam</hi> in derision said,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 3.21.</note>
                  <hi>Behold the man like one of vs is made;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The sonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> now of God may say,</l>
               <l>Behold he's made like one of vs to day,</l>
               <l>Not only like to vs but euen the same:</l>
               <l>All that belongs to this our mortall frame</l>
               <l>He tooke, saue that which made it mortall, sinne,</l>
               <l>Wer't not for which, man had immortall beene.</l>
               <l>Yea sinne it selfe he tooke (<note n="*" place="margin">Isai. 53.4.</note>
                  <hi>as truth doth say</hi>)</l>
               <l>But tooke it only to take it away.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.3.4.</note>
                  <hi>Similitude of sinfull flesh araies</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Godhead, so sinne in the flesh he slaies.</l>
               <l>Similitude of sinfull flesh he takes,</l>
               <l>But yet in taking it this diffrence makes,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Accepit car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is veritatem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on similitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em, accepit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eccati simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itudinem non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eritatem.</note>The Flesh he takes in truth, with flesh indu'de,</l>
               <l>The sinne he takes but in Similitude.</l>
               <l>The flesh he takes is ours, but so he takes it</l>
               <l>As that his owne, and cleane from sinne he makes it.</l>
               <l>The sinne he takes is ours, and not his owne,</l>
               <l>For sinne in him saue ours was neuer knowne:</l>
               <l>The flesh he takes for euer to enioy it,</l>
               <l>The sinne he takes but onlie to destroy it.</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2263:14"/>
               <l>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note>
                  <hi>He knew no sinne, yet sinne was made, that we,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The righteousnesse of God in him might be.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Both what he made and made not he did take,</l>
               <l>Flesh, which he made: sin which he nere did make:</l>
               <l>That which he neuer made and doth detest,</l>
               <l>He would be made for vs to make vs blest.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord what is man that only for his sake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' Almighty should such strange exchanges make?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The royallest exchange for vs was this,</l>
               <l>When God chang'd his for ours, we ours for his.</l>
               <l>When that man might be freed, God would be sold,</l>
               <l>When for our brasse he gaue in change his gold:</l>
               <l>When with his royall robes vs to adorne,</l>
               <l>To take on him our rags he did not scorne.</l>
               <l>O royall change for vs, ô blessed Burse,</l>
               <l>Where man the blessing gaines, God takes the curse!</l>
               <l>Cease we not then with blessed spirits to sing</l>
               <l>An holy Anthem to our heauenly King,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Proud <hi>Carnall</hi> reason, strike the swelling sailes</l>
               <l>Of humane wisedome which here nought availes:</l>
               <l>Vnder the lee of true religion fall,</l>
               <l>In this aduenture<note n="†" place="margin">These my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries cannot comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by reas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they must b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> apprehende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by Faith.</note> Faith doth all in all.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note>
                  <hi>Great is this Mysterie of Godlinesse,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Transcending mans dwarf-wit.<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc myste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> um miraculi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> plenum est, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> scitè &amp; rite Bernard. Vni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> idem{que} opus m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> sericordia &amp; iustitia: vna eadem{que} Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sona Deus &amp; homo. Vna ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dem{que} faemin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mater &amp; vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go: Vnus idem{que} filius <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> vnas idem{que} Christus nobi &amp; iudex &amp; advocatus.</note>Who can expresse,</l>
               <l>Who can conceaue how Earth should heauen inuest,</l>
               <l>How God in flesh should be made manifest?</l>
               <l>How Iustice should in sweet coniunction</l>
               <l>With Mercie meet in the same action:</l>
               <l>How the same Person God and man should be,</l>
               <l>Yet neither Nature loose his propertie:</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2263:15"/>
               <l>How the same Sonne should Father haue &amp; mother,</l>
               <l>And yet be said to haue nor one nor other:</l>
               <l>How the same woman trulie may be said</l>
               <l>At once to be a mother and a maid:</l>
               <l>How mothers milk into her brests should come,</l>
               <l>Who nere receau'd mans seed within her womb:</l>
               <l>How God from heauen should come to joine with clay,</l>
               <l>Yet God with God in heauen should euer stay.</l>
               <l>The heathen wisards, though they did avow</l>
               <l>Men to be Gods, yet neuer would allow</l>
               <l>God to be man, supposing God would scorne</l>
               <l>In a poore mortall vessell to be borne;</l>
               <l>(And reason sure will say: As eas'lie can</l>
               <l>Man become God as God become a man)</l>
               <l>Yea they who best iudg'd of the Deitie</l>
               <l>Would soon'st of all deride this mysterie:</l>
               <l>That he who immortalitie possesses</l>
               <l>Would become mortall: He who others blesses</l>
               <l>And is most blest himselfe, would be a<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note>
                  <hi>Curse,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(For who would change a good estate for worse)</l>
               <l>That he who Thunders in the Clouds on high,</l>
               <l>Become an Infant, in a Cratch should crie:</l>
               <l>That Heauens Lord Paramount should thus become</l>
               <l>A subject, and possesse a servants roome:</l>
               <l>That the Law-giuer, who from Law is free,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">made vnder the Law. Gal. 4.4.</note>
                  <hi>An vnderling vnto the Law should be:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And this not for his friends but euen for those,</l>
               <l>Who of his friends became his mortall foes,</l>
               <l>That so they might for euer friends remaine,</l>
               <l>Though by their friendship he can neuer gaine</l>
               <l>The least of that it cost him to procure it,</l>
               <l>And in such fraile ones firmely to ensure it.</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2263:15"/>
               <l>(Sith 'tis against the rules of Policie</l>
               <l>To trust a reconciled Enemie)</l>
               <l>Yet all this, wretched man to blisse to bring,</l>
               <l>He hath perform'd. Then cease we not to sing</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come Faith and fathome the profundities</l>
               <l>Of these so secret sacred mysteries:</l>
               <l>The line of Reason is too short to sound</l>
               <l>This Sea, which neither bottome hath nor bound.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Hîc human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cessat ratio, hîc flaccessit acies intellect<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us nostri: hîc docti pariter indocti{que} con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunguntur. Heiu sius ho. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Theophan.</note>All learning here is pos'd, all witt to seeke:</l>
               <l>Doctors and Dunces here are learn'd alike.</l>
               <l>The wisest here no wiser are then fooles:</l>
               <l>* <hi>Christ in a Stall was borne not in the Schooles:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Birth by th' Angel was not first made knowne,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Rabbies,</hi> but to Shepheards showne;</l>
               <l>People who in simplicitie did liue:</l>
               <l>Dispute they could not, but they could beleeue.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vnto this feast which was for all men fitted,</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Christus non in Academiâ natus est sed in stabulo. ibid.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Wisemen were the last that were admitted:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who humbly did fall downe when they were come</l>
               <l>Their humane wisdome they did leaue at home;</l>
               <l>And this their great Inviter more contented,</l>
               <l>Then all the pretious presents they presented:</l>
               <l>For Wisdome doth her feast for none prepare,</l>
               <l>Saue those who of their owne first emptie are:</l>
               <l>Those she doth fill: but such as filled come</l>
               <l>With their owne Wisdome, she sends empty home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come we with them, and let Faith come with vs,</l>
               <l>Which doth beleeue, adore, and not discusse.</l>
               <l>A better present to our heauenly King</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Gold,</hi> then <hi>Myrhe,</hi> then <hi>Frankinsence</hi> we bring:</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:2263:16"/>
               <l>All which Faith offers when it doth beleeue</l>
               <l>The deed, and to the doer praise doth giue,</l>
               <l>For that whereof it can no reason render.</l>
               <l>The true beleeuer is the best commender</l>
               <l>Of Gods all wondrous works, most glory bringing,</l>
               <l>When with the blessed spirits he fals a singing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Demus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aliquid posse, cuius nos rationem red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere non pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumus. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin.</note>Grant we that God can something doe, which man</l>
               <l>Can neuet reach with reasons narrow span:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Si potest ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo intelligere diuina, potest &amp; facere. Nam intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere est quasi è vestigio sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequi. Lactant. Institut. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>Could man of all the actions God can doe,</l>
               <l>The reason render, he might doe them too.</l>
               <l>(For none Omniscient can be but one,</l>
               <l>Who also is Omnipotent alone.)</l>
               <l>And could man doe Gods actions, man should be</l>
               <l>Omnipotent, and God, as well as he.</l>
               <l>Gods works to vs apparent are, the way</l>
               <l>Whereby he works, clos'd in himselfe doth stay:</l>
               <l>So doth some skilfull Artizan reveale</l>
               <l>His Maister-peece, but doth his skill conceale:</l>
               <l>So God his works doth vnto mortals show,</l>
               <l>But how he works, he doth not let them know:</l>
               <l>Least if they knew both Art and worke, they might</l>
               <l>The Art, the worke, the worker basely slight.</l>
               <l>Those works doe quickly starue their estimation,</l>
               <l>Which are not fed and fil'd with admiration.</l>
               <l>Praise is but cold which from a tongue is sent,</l>
               <l>Not warm'd with wonder and astonishment:</l>
               <l>But when we stand amazed at the deed,</l>
               <l>Best praise vnto the doer doth proceed</l>
               <l>From wondring silence. Then at last we straine</l>
               <l>Our tongues to sing out some Angellike vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2263:16"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Avaunt then saucie Curiositie,</l>
               <l>Dangerous it is into this Arke to prie.<note place="margin">Against Curi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>osity.</note>
               </l>
               <l>God soonest doth his mysteries impart,</l>
               <l>Vnto the humble and beleeuing heart.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Inueniet pi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us pulsator quod curiosus indagator no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> poterit. Bern. in Cant. ser. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note>The humble suter soonest shall obtaine,</l>
               <l>That which the curious searcher seeks in vaine:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Qui scruta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor est Maiest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atis, opprime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à gloriâ</note>Let him who diues into Gods secresie,</l>
               <l>Dread overwhelming by his Majestie.</l>
               <l>Here nothing doth sound knowledg more advance,</l>
               <l>Nor is more learn'd then humble Ignorance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Will <hi>Adams Imps</hi> nere from this itch be quitted,</l>
               <l>Of craving to know more then is permitted?</l>
               <l>What fool'd their Father out of all his store</l>
               <l>Of wisdome, but this lusting after more?</l>
               <l>While he would wiser be then he was made,</l>
               <l>He lost the substance catching at the shade;</l>
               <l>Yet will not his bold issue warned be,</l>
               <l>But still are tasting the forbidden Tree.</l>
               <l>As if a blind man sought his sight to finde,</l>
               <l>By the same meanes which made his Father blind:</l>
               <l>Cease then to argue, or if you dispute,</l>
               <l>Let Faith be moderator, reason mute.</l>
               <l>'Twere hard for me, and many a silly man,</l>
               <l>Wer't Art, and Witt that made a Christian,</l>
               <l>Not Faith, and Hope, and Charity. Those three</l>
               <l>As well in simple, as in wise may be.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Benedicta sit diuina sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia, quae in negotio salutis humanam pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus excludit. Heiusius vbi supr.</note>
                  <hi>Blest be Gods wisdome who doth mans exclude</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In heauenly matters.</hi> Here the raw and rude</l>
               <l>May with the wisest walke. The wisest man</l>
               <l>Can but beleeue, and so the simplest can.</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2263:17"/>
               <l>Yea sometimes sooner then the wiser doe,</l>
               <l>Who carnall wisdome trusting too much to,</l>
               <l>Runne mad with reason, and then furiously,</l>
               <l>Doe cut the knott they know not to vntie.</l>
               <l>Tis well that God this wondrous worke hath done,</l>
               <l>Whereby to Vs is brought Saluation:</l>
               <l>Sufficeth that the matter is reveal'd,</l>
               <l>Although the manner be from vs conceal'd:</l>
               <l>Tis well the benefit doth ours remaine,</l>
               <l>Though to the secret we can not attaine:</l>
               <l>Tis faire our King into his Court doth take vs,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Hall. B. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>Though of his Counsell he refuse to make vs.</l>
               <l>Each Saint may say, such honour is for me</l>
               <l>Too high. Yet all his Saints so honoured be.</l>
               <l>Then let his praise still in their mouthes be found,</l>
               <l>And let them with his royall Guard resound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Powre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d praise of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th.</note>O blest be God who giues Faith to supply,</l>
               <l>That which for Reasons reach is farre too high:</l>
               <l>Which man aboue himselfe to mount doth teach,</l>
               <l>Reaching to what surmounteth humane reach.</l>
               <l>Whereby a Christian doth excell the rest</l>
               <l>Of Men, as farre as Man excels a beast.</l>
               <l>Saies God the word? Faith doubts not of the deed,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ai. 53.19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>atres gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tio Christi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> arrari non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>test Credi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>test, &amp; vbi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gua deficit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ides proficit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aximus ubi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>How farre so ere it doth mans sence exceed:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Christs generation cannot be declar'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beleeu'd it can be. Nothing is too hard</l>
               <l>For Faith. Where witt and language both doe faile,</l>
               <l>To thinke, to speake, Faith coms and doth prevaile.</l>
               <l>What Art by arguing cannot comprehend,</l>
               <l>Faith by beleeuing soone doth apprehend.</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2263:17"/>
               <l>Things whereof t'is impossible to giue</l>
               <l>A reason, Faith doth easily beleeue.</l>
               <l>Faith made the Man-vntouched Virgins wombe,<note place="margin">Ipsa corusca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tis monitis s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cra virgo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nistri Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, at{que} ideo concepit cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um: credente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nam Christu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> adit, dubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile pectus si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titubante fid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> vacuo conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nit honore Prudentius Apotheos: Compendium salutis est fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Fidei ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staculum sap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>entia. Heiu si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. <hi>1. Cor. 1.26.</hi> Omnia in D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> supra ration<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nihil supra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dem. Quicquid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus Deus pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> facere, sola <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des potest cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dere. He ius<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> vt supr.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To swell, and milke vnto her breasts to come.</l>
               <l>Had she not first by Faith the word receau'd</l>
               <l>Into her soule, her wombe had beene bereau'd,</l>
               <l>Of that preferment to conceaue the Word,</l>
               <l>Which to the world Saluation doth afford.</l>
               <l>Faith made the Virgin pregnant, Faith must make,</l>
               <l>The Christian Christ into his soule to take:</l>
               <l>As she by Faith conceaued him, so He</l>
               <l>By Faith in Christians still conceau'd must be.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faith to Saluation's a compendious way,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wisdome to Faith an obstacle and stay.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> nor mighty God doth chuse,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor any that hath Faith he doth refuse.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O let me wise vnto Saluation be!</l>
               <l>Lord, giue me Faith, take Witt who will for me!</l>
               <l>All things in God doe humane witt transcend,</l>
               <l>But nothing Faith. Where humane Witt doth end,</l>
               <l>Let Faith supply. What only God can doe,</l>
               <l>Faith only can beleeue and reach vnto.</l>
               <l>The things which God hath done for vs today,</l>
               <l>Conceaue we cannot, but beleeue we may.</l>
               <l>And if we doe beleeue, let's not dispute,</l>
               <l>But speake our Faith in accents which doe sute</l>
               <l>Vnto the message which one Angel bringing,</l>
               <l>Immediately a multitude are singing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.12</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Into this myst'rie they to looke desire,</l>
               <l>And looking doe not argue but admire.</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2263:18"/>
               <l>Solemnizing the Day whose like before</l>
               <l>They neuer saw, they neuer shall see more.</l>
               <l>An holy, happy day, a day of dayes,</l>
               <l>Greater then any day, whose radiant rayes</l>
               <l>Had they not shin'd and brought this blessed light,</l>
               <l>The world had laine drown'd in eternall night.</l>
               <l>Better for vs, vile Wretches, it had beene,</l>
               <l>T' haue seene no daies, thē this day not t'haue seene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Day of dayes which in due estimation,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iores sunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in quibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eternam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am renasci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quam illi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uibus ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tempora creamur: fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunt bona <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiae quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urae. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rius ho. <hi>2.</hi> paschate <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n. 12.46.</hi>
                  </note>Excels the first dayes of the worlds Creation!</l>
               <l>Not all the works which those six daies brought forth</l>
               <l>Can equallize this one daies works for worth.</l>
               <l>Then, out of darknesse God did light disclose</l>
               <l>Now he himselfe is come a light that those</l>
               <l>Who sate in darknesse and death's dreery shade,</l>
               <l>Might find the way that vnto life is made.</l>
               <l>Then did he o're the Earth the Heauens extend:</l>
               <l>Now Heauen it selfe vouchsafeth to descend,</l>
               <l>And kisse the Earth and kindly to embrace it,</l>
               <l>And with it selfe 'boue highest heigth to place it.</l>
               <l>Then after his owne Image God did frame</l>
               <l>The last of Creatures whom he Man did name:</l>
               <l>Now after mans owne Image he doth make</l>
               <l>Himselfe, and our Similitude doth take.</l>
               <l>Himselfe is made that which he made, that he</l>
               <l>Might what he made from finall marring free.</l>
               <l>All things of nothing then he made, but here</l>
               <l>We are new made who worse then nothing were.</l>
               <l>He spake the Word, and all things were made then,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hn. 1.14.</note>
                  <hi>Now is the word made flesh and dwels with men.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That men made spirit who were but flesh before,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 6.7.</note>With him one spirit might be for evermore:</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2263:18"/>
               <l>The Angels shouted at the worlds Creation,<note place="margin">Iob. 38.7.</note>
               </l>
               <l>More joyfully they sing for th' Incarnation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Diuine Nature our fraile Nature takes,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.4.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And of his Nature vs partakers makes.</l>
               <l>God of a Virgin pure is borne, thereby</l>
               <l>To purge mans foule impure nativitie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Bread of Life</hi> is in a Manger lay'd,</l>
               <l>That Man (become a beast because he stray'd</l>
               <l>From his Creator, now by grace restor'd</l>
               <l>T' a better state then nature could afford)</l>
               <l>Might with this heauenly Provender be fed:</l>
               <l>Come Man and eat of this most blessed Bread;</l>
               <l>(Bread, which did more then all the worlds worth cost,</l>
               <l>And gather vp the crums that none be lost:</l>
               <l>One crum of this doth farre that Feast surpasse,</l>
               <l>Which by th' <hi>Assyrian Monarch</hi> once made was:<note place="margin">Hest. 1.3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Come nere so many none shall hungrie rise,</l>
               <l>This only loafe all commers shall suffice.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Manna</hi> of Eternall mercie fals</l>
               <l>In full abundance, and for gatherers cals:</l>
               <l>That man with food of Angels may be fed,</l>
               <l>And vnto life Eternall nourished:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come yee that hunger, gather vp this Man,</l>
               <l>Which who so eates againe nere hunger can,</l>
               <l>Yet hungers still. More hunger doth arise</l>
               <l>From this sweet food the more it satisfies.</l>
               <l>And let not him that feedeth feare or think,</l>
               <l>That to his bread and food he shall want drink:</l>
               <l>He who is food our hunger to expell,</l>
               <l>Is against thirst an euer-springing well:</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2263:19"/>
               <l>There goes &amp; flowes from this celestiall Moūtaine,</l>
               <l>Bread against hunger and against thirst a Fountaine.</l>
               <l>Drink of this Fountaine which who so once tasteth</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 4.</note>Shall neuer thirst. This Fountaine neuer wasteth:</l>
               <l>But is to them who drink a water springing</l>
               <l>To life Eternall, and them thither bringing.</l>
               <l>A double vertue this one Fountaine hath,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Zacchar. 13.1</note>It quencheth thirst, and also is a Bath</l>
               <l>To wash and clense vs from our sins pollution,</l>
               <l>That so our filth may not be our confusion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come, euerie <hi>Naaman,</hi> and here bath, thereby</l>
               <l>To wash away thy soules foule leprosie:</l>
               <l>And being made cleane beware thou sinne no more,</l>
               <l>Least worse ensue then that which went before:</l>
               <l>But with the thankfull leaper turne againe,</l>
               <l>And with thy clenser euer more remaine:</l>
               <l>Rendring him thanks and singing forth his praise,</l>
               <l>Ioyning with th' Angels in their heauenly layes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Christ our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eace. Ephes. 2.14. The way. The truth. The life. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 14.16.</note>To day wars end, and Peace begins: To day</l>
               <l>Wandring doth cease; for we haue found the way:</l>
               <l>Falshood's remou'd; for Truth to light is brought,</l>
               <l>Death perisheth, for life to day is wrought.</l>
               <l>Now life begins to liue. To liue said I,</l>
               <l>Nay rather now life doth begin to die:</l>
               <l>God who is life, mans life did therefore take,</l>
               <l>That he a way to his owne death might make.</l>
               <l>Vnlesse he man become he cannot die,</l>
               <l>Unlesse he die, we die Eternally.</l>
               <l>Rather then we should suffer endlesse paine,</l>
               <l>He would be borne of purpose to be slaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2263:19"/>
               <l>Think not that Christ did then begin to suffer</l>
               <l>When Iudas sold him,<note place="margin">Christs pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on began <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his incarna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. Isai. 53.10</note> and the Iewes did offer</l>
               <l>To apprehend him. He did then begin</l>
               <l>To make his soule a sacrifice for sinne</l>
               <l>When he took bodie. He began to die</l>
               <l>Then, when assuming our mortalitie</l>
               <l>He made himselfe one able to be slaine.</l>
               <l>To put on man is but to put on paine.</l>
               <l>His death was at his Birth, he then began</l>
               <l>To die, when he begun to put on man:</l>
               <l>This flowre ere it sprang forth began to fade,</l>
               <l>Thus was his Crosse before his cradle made:</l>
               <l>The drops of bloud which at his death he shed</l>
               <l>Were but his Infant-drops of teares dy'd red.</l>
               <l>His swathing cloathes did with that linnen meet,</l>
               <l>Whereof good <hi>Ioseph</hi> made his winding sheet.</l>
               <l>His bloud was as a Salue bespred thereon,</l>
               <l>This Plaister cures our soules corruption.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Behold how he a tender Infant cries,</l>
               <l>Who wipes all teares from true repentant eyes!</l>
               <l>O let vs of this Infant learne to weepe,</l>
               <l>That from Eternall teares he may vs keepe!</l>
               <l>Restore o man the groneing which he lent,</l>
               <l>Restore the teares which he for thee hath spent.</l>
               <l>Consider how much thou to him doest owe,</l>
               <l>Who would for thee a double suffring know,</l>
               <l>Suffring for thee who wert a wretch forelorne</l>
               <l>Worst at his death, but first in being borne.</l>
               <l>What should not we suffer for him, who thus</l>
               <l>Hath from Eternall suffrings freed vs?</l>
               <l>Who therefore wept for vs that we might sing,</l>
               <l>With holy Angels to our heauenly King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2263:20"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What is for mans saluation left vndone,</l>
               <l>Sith God to vs hath sent his only Sonne?</l>
               <l>That euer deerelie loued Sonne of his,</l>
               <l>In whom alone the Father pleased is.</l>
               <l>A Sonne who by his comming doth restore</l>
               <l>All that our Father <hi>Adam</hi> lost, and more.</l>
               <l>This Sonne of God made Sonne of man we see,</l>
               <l>That Sonnes of men made Sonnes of God might be.</l>
               <l>High is made low, and honour is embas'de</l>
               <l>That so the base to honour may be rais'd:</l>
               <l>Fulnesse growes emptie emptinesse to fill,</l>
               <l>And wisedome childish to giue children skill.</l>
               <l>Freedome it selfe doth bondage vndertake</l>
               <l>T'enfranchize those whom sin did bondslaues make:</l>
               <l>The Roabe of righteousnesse is naked borne,</l>
               <l>The naked with his righteous Roabes t'adorne:</l>
               <l>Strength is made low, &amp; weaknesse strength hath found,</l>
               <l>The richest poore, that beggars might abound</l>
               <l>In the best riches, and life learnes to die</l>
               <l>That so the dead may liue Eternallie:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat is man that only for his sake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' Almighty should such strange exchanges make?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What can poore mortals in requitall bring?</l>
               <l>Nothing. Yet with Heauens Quiristers wee'l sing,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God on high, on Earth be Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let good will t'wards Christians neuer cease.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2263:20"/>
            <head>On this present worke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen every common writer that but dares</l>
               <l>Preferre his pen to waite on the affaires</l>
               <l>Of vertues Clients, gets himselfe a name.</l>
               <l>And reputation by that courteous fame</l>
               <l>He giues to others: and what he bestowes</l>
               <l>On their iust merits, thankefully ore-flowes</l>
               <l>To his owne praise; Then, what may you expect?</l>
               <l>(Graue oracle of witt) that doe select</l>
               <l>No lesse a Theame then Gods nativity,</l>
               <l>To be the subiect of your History:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Baies is too meane a garland to empale</l>
               <l>Such sacred temples: mortall praise too fraile</l>
               <l>To sound such worth: Earth nothing hath to even</l>
               <l>Such merits, but must owe your paye to Heaven.</l>
               <l>Where for a Lawrell, you shall haue a Crowne,</l>
               <l>And everlasting glory for renowne.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Advertisement to the Readers.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HEnce all prophane! ther's nothing here,</l>
               <l>That can delight a wicked eare:</l>
               <l>No wanton flashes, to make sin</l>
               <l>Seeme sweet to him that ioyes therein:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2263:21"/>
               <l>No loose conceits, to flatter vice,</l>
               <l>And make Hell thought a Paradise:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All that is here, is pure and high,</l>
               <l>And locked vp in mystery;</l>
               <l>Nor can be rightly vnderstood,</l>
               <l>But of such only as be good.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. B. ex A.A. A.M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2263:21"/>
            <head>HOLY RAPTVRES IN CONTEMPLATING SOME OF THE MOST OB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SERVABLE ADIVNCTS ABOVT OVR SAVIOVRS <hi>NATIVITIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The season of the Yeare wherein our Sauiour was Borne, namely in the <hi>Winter-solstice</hi> or <hi>Sun-steade.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow seemes the Sunnes vnwearied Waggonere,<note place="margin">A discripti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of the Win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> solstice.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who every day surrounds the Earthly Sphere,</l>
                  <l>To Make a stand, and breath his restlesse teames,</l>
                  <l>Which through the World convey his golden beames.</l>
                  <l>Nor doth the Day to our appearance seeme</l>
                  <l>As yet his captiue-minutes to redeeme</l>
                  <l>From the prevailing Night, but doth begin</l>
                  <l>To steale thereon and some advantage win.</l>
                  <l>Henceforth the night shall loose, the day shall gaine,</l>
                  <l>Nor will the Sister long in debt remaine</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:2263:22"/>
                  <l>Unto her Brother, but will surely pay</l>
                  <l>Some part of what she borrowed every day;</l>
                  <l>Till both be euen. This season of the Yeare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Did our Eternall Sunne</hi> chuse to appeare</l>
                  <l>In our <hi>Horizon,</hi> our Day to restore,</l>
                  <l>Which sinnes incroaching Night abridg'd before</l>
                  <l>In Summers <hi>Aequinoctial</hi> conceau'd,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ceptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> est in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>inoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> verno, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in Solstitio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erno. Et in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ceptione e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate dies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pit incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tum, &amp; scente vera <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> lucis &amp; augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r officium. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>gust. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ap. Ser. <hi>22.</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e noctis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>na in dici seunt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Eucher. <hi>2.</hi> De Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In Winter-sun-stead borne; We were bereau'd</l>
                  <l>Of gladsome Day invellop'd in sad Night,</l>
                  <l>Till this bright Starre arose and brought vs Light.</l>
                  <l>Thus did our Day at his Conception,</l>
                  <l>And at his Birth take augmentation.</l>
                  <l>When such a Light into the world is sent,</l>
                  <l>How can the Night but shrink, the Day augment?</l>
                  <l>All-haile ô holy, happy, heauenly Day,</l>
                  <l>That turn'st our Winter into joyfull May.</l>
                  <l>And springing makest an eternall Spring,</l>
                  <l>Where earst sins Autumne a sad fall did bring:</l>
                  <l>A Day that makest euerlasting Summer,</l>
                  <l>By the approaching of this heauenly commer:</l>
                  <l>Who did from Heauen to Earth so kindly come,</l>
                  <l>That Earth in Heauen by Him might haue a roome:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O were it Winter-solstice once with me,</l>
                  <l>That this sins night no more increas'd might be!</l>
                  <l>But that the blessed Day of Reformation,</l>
                  <l>In me might find a joyfull augmentation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Sunne of righteousnesse who would'st appeare,</l>
                  <l>In shortest, saddest season of the yeare.</l>
                  <l>Who<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eb. 1.3.</note> being <hi>Brightnes</hi> would'st in <hi>Black-mon'th</hi> come,</l>
                  <l>That by thy comming all might bright become.</l>
                  <l>Come vnto me, come into me, that I</l>
                  <l>To <hi>righteousnesse</hi> may liue, to sinne may die.</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2263:22"/>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Black-mon'th</hi> still with me because of sinne:</l>
                  <l>O come that I might bright become within:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come, that the Night of sinne may shrinke in me,</l>
                  <l>And that the Day of grace encreas'd may be.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The time of his Birth. By Night.</head>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>THE Light which shines in darknesse</hi> coms by Night,</l>
               <l>Those that did sit in darknesse to enlight.</l>
               <l>What meanes the Day-star in the Night to rise?</l>
               <l>To shew that he giues light to blindest eyes.</l>
               <l>To shew that he the Worlds Light is, who may</l>
               <l>Turne the most gloomy Night to gladsome Day.</l>
               <l>But why doth Truth that neuer shuns the light,</l>
               <l>Come like a Theefe in darknesse of the Night?</l>
               <l>To make both commings, first and last, t' agree,</l>
               <l>That they (who him expect) should watchfull be.</l>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Aliter de eodem argumento.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHAT? Is it Night with our <hi>Antipodes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That thus by Night the Sunne to vs doth rise?</l>
                     <l>It should be so. The Sunne though bright he be,</l>
                     <l>Neuer at once doth the Worlds both sides see:</l>
                     <l>But our pure Sunne aboue shines and below,</l>
                     <l>And no <hi>Antipodes</hi> at all doth know.</l>
                     <l>This Sunne which now at Night doth rise, is he</l>
                     <l>Who neuer sets, but rising still doth see.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Come glorious Sunne, spread thine illustrious light</l>
                     <l>On me, who wholy darknesse am, and Night!</l>
                     <l>My darknesse turne to light, my night to day,</l>
                     <l>That so eternall darknesse shun I may!</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2263:23"/>
                     <l>And of that blessed Light with thee partake,</l>
                     <l>Whose luster everlasting Day doth make.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The Place of his Birth. A Stall.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 49.20.</note>MAN being in honour had not vnderstanding,</l>
                  <l>But turned Beast from his Creator wandring:</l>
                  <l>Him to restore and to make man againe,</l>
                  <l>God to be borne 'mongst Beasts doth not disdaine.</l>
                  <l>His Mothers Child-bed Chamber is a Stall,</l>
                  <l>A Cratch his Cradle, and the Lord of all</l>
                  <l>For his poore Parent ready to lie downe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">There was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o roome for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>m in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nne. Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 7.</note>Cannot Command an <hi>Inne</hi> in all the Towne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vncivile Cittizens, and People vild,</l>
                  <l>Thus to exclude a Woman great with Child</l>
                  <l>So neere her time! Had you humanitie,</l>
                  <l>You would haue shew'd to such more courtesie.</l>
                  <l>You would for such a one haue found a place,</l>
                  <l>Thinking it might haue beene your Mothers case:</l>
                  <l>Rather then she should in a Stall remaine,</l>
                  <l>Your selues vpon the cold ground should haue laine.</l>
                  <l>Are there not still such <hi>Innes,</hi> to whom no Ghuest,</l>
                  <l>Lesse welcome is then Christ, who is the best?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sweet Sauiour, I an <hi>Inne-keeper</hi> will be,</l>
                  <l>The signe shall be my Heart; Come lodge with me.</l>
                  <l>The damned crue I entertain'd before,</l>
                  <l>(My roaring sinnes) I'le all turne out of dore:</l>
                  <l>I'le not afford them lodging in a Stall,</l>
                  <l>Thou shalt haue <hi>Parlor, Chamber, Hall</hi> and all.</l>
                  <l>The best cheere that I can I will prepare</l>
                  <l>For thee. And this shall be my cheifest care,</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:2263:23"/>
                  <l>(Because I know 'tis that which likes thee best)</l>
                  <l>That all be neat and cleane for such a Ghuest.</l>
                  <l>Thou, who when first thou cam'st would'st in no bed</l>
                  <l>Saue a pure Virgins wombe repose thy head;</l>
                  <l>Thou who in all thy life lou'd'st puritie,</l>
                  <l>And being dead would'st in pure linnen lie.</l>
                  <l>Thou who compared Art vnto a Doue,</l>
                  <l>The Bird who neatnesse doth and cleanenesse loue.</l>
                  <l>I know that he who shall thee entertaine,</l>
                  <l>Must cheifly care that all be neat and cleane.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then how can I hope thou wilt lodge with me,</l>
                  <l>In whom all things so foule and sordid be?</l>
                  <l>Yet come and lodge. For why? I know 'tis true,</l>
                  <l>That where thou com'st<note n="e" place="margin">Reuel. 21. 2. Cor. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> thou makest' all things new</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou whose Birth a Stall could stellifie,</l>
                  <l>With Heauen within, and a bright starre on high,</l>
                  <l>That not the best <hi>Star-chamber</hi> of them all,</l>
                  <l>For glory could compare with this <hi>Star-stall.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O grace me with thy Presence who art able,</l>
                  <l>To make a Pallace of th' <hi>Augaean Stable.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou who had'st things of no better worth,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Straw</hi> and <hi>Hay</hi> to set thy Chamber forth.</l>
                  <l>Where thou wert borne. Be borne in me this Day,</l>
                  <l>In me poore wretch who with'red am like <hi>Hay.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Be borne in me: so shall this <hi>Hay</hi> be made,</l>
                  <l>Fresh as the <hi>Rose</hi> and neuer after fade.</l>
               </lg>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Aliter.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>ART thou so humble Lord, thou doest not scorne,</l>
                     <l>To be 'mong Oxen, and 'mong Asses borne?</l>
                     <l>O scorne not me, who am become (alasse!)</l>
                     <l>More brutish, foolish then the Oxe or Asse.</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:2263:24"/>
                     <l>For they, (poore Beasts!) their owner know, we see,</l>
                     <l>But farre more brutish I haue not knowne thee.</l>
                     <l>Thou mad'st me first a man, a noble Creature,</l>
                     <l>Little inferiour to th' Angellike Nature:</l>
                     <l>But I through sinne into a state did throwe</l>
                     <l>My selfe then brutish Creatures farre below.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be borne in me, that being borne againe</l>
                     <l>In thee, a new borne Creature may remaine.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>IIII.</hi> The Publishing of his Birth. First vnto Shepheards.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 2.8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.10.</note>TO <hi>Shepheards</hi> is his Birth first signified,</l>
                  <l>Who by their flocks night watching did abide.</l>
                  <l>To shew that the <hi>great Shepheard</hi> now is borne,</l>
                  <l>Who no base office for his Sheepe will scorne:</l>
                  <l>But watching o're his flock doth still remaine,</l>
                  <l>And they must watch who will him entertaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come let vs with these joyfull <hi>Shepheards</hi> hie</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Cratch, where this sweet <hi>Babe</hi> doth lie;</l>
                  <l>That is, his <hi>Church:</hi> This place doth still afford,</l>
                  <l>This heauenly Infant swathed in his Word:</l>
                  <l>Let vs when there he doth his words impart,</l>
                  <l>Lay them vp all with <hi>Marie</hi> in our heart.</l>
                  <l>More blest by bearing them she did become,</l>
                  <l>Then by her bearing him within her wombe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O blessed Man who in his heart doth swathe,</l>
                  <l>And bind vp sure his Word. For he that hath</l>
                  <l>His word hath him. The word it selfe is He,</l>
                  <l>Then where his word is, needs himselfe must be.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:2263:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> The Publisher of his Birth. A blessed Angel.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 2.9.</note>A <hi>Glorious Angel</hi> is the Referendarie,</l>
                  <l>Who first these tidings vnto men doth carrie.</l>
                  <l>An heauenly Herald fittest was to bring,</l>
                  <l>Newes of the comming of the heauenly King.</l>
                  <l>That Gospel by an Angel first was brought</l>
                  <l>To Man, which now by Man to men is taught.</l>
                  <l>That Gospel which God now by vs doth teach.</l>
                  <l>No glorious Angel is too good to Preach.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O let Gods Ministers as they are stil'd,</l>
                  <l>Angels, be like the Angels vndefil'd!</l>
                  <l>Let them not with an earthly life defame,</l>
                  <l>The reputation of an heauenly name:</l>
                  <l>But striue they others to excell so farre,</l>
                  <l>As Angels vnto them superior are:</l>
                  <l>That whereas others are but men at best,</l>
                  <l>They may like Angels shine aboue the rest.</l>
                  <l>What is heauens greatest greife, earths greatest euill?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An Angels place possessed by a Divel.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O let not an vnholy conversation,</l>
                  <l>Fowly belie an holy appellation!</l>
                  <l>Holy the function we may well repute,</l>
                  <l>Which holy Angels joy to execute:</l>
                  <l>Holy he is, the holiest of all,</l>
                  <l>Who doth vs to the holy function call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Holy the message is which we must doe,</l>
                  <l>O let the Messengers bee holy too.</l>
               </lg>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2263:25"/>
                  <head>Aliter.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HOW glorious is the newes, how full of joy,</l>
                     <l>In which God none but Angels will imploy?</l>
                     <l>How gladly doe these fierie Posts attend,</l>
                     <l>When for mans good their Maker will them send?</l>
                     <l>No message they more willingly goe on,</l>
                     <l>Then that which tends to mans saluation.</l>
                     <l>An Angel first is vnto <hi>Marie</hi> sent,</l>
                     <l>T' acquaint her with his heauenly Lords intent:</l>
                     <l>Who of all <hi>Maids</hi> made choyce of her, that she</l>
                     <l>Should both a <hi>Maiden</hi> and a <hi>Mother</hi> be.</l>
                     <l>And that of all her sex God had decreed,</l>
                     <l>This woman should bring forth the womans seed.</l>
                     <l>Who promis'd was that cursed Head to bruise,</l>
                     <l>Which first the sillie woman did seduce.</l>
                     <l>An Angel settles <hi>Iosephs</hi> doubting thought,</l>
                     <l>Tels him, the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> this worke had wrought,</l>
                     <l>He need not feare her for his Wife to take,</l>
                     <l>Whom God not man, did thus a mother make.</l>
                     <l>An Angel bids him into <hi>Egypt</hi> goe,</l>
                     <l>To saue his life who first his Birth did shew:</l>
                     <l>And when the <hi>Infant-slayer</hi> had breath'd his last,</l>
                     <l>An Angel wils him home againe to hast.</l>
                     <l>An Angel first this gladsome Gospell preaches,</l>
                     <l>A few poore <hi>Shepheards</hi> th' <hi>Audience</hi> whom hee teaches,</l>
                     <l>Nere was such distance in regard of glory,</l>
                     <l>Betweene a<note n="*" place="margin">Preacher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o was only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>reature.</note>
                        <hi>Preacher</hi> and his <hi>Auditorie.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Why should the greatest Doctor now disdaine,</l>
                     <l>To be a Preacher to the simplest Swaine?</l>
                     <l>If he who sends vs no respecter be,</l>
                     <l>Of Persons (<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ct. 10.34.</note> as he saith) then why should we?</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2263:25"/>
                     <l>Looke we, when on our message we are bent,</l>
                     <l>Not vnto whom, but from whom we are sent.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As welcome vnto heauen is he, that brings</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Shepheards soule, as he that doth a Kings.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 131.14.</note>The Celebration of his Birth, by a multitude of Angels.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE Sermon ended is, the Psalme ensues,</l>
                  <l>A Psalme that suteth with the joyfull newes.</l>
                  <l>The subject of the Sermon Preacht by one:</l>
                  <l>A multitude begins when one hath done.</l>
                  <l>An Hoast of Heauenly Quiristers doe sing</l>
                  <l>A joyfull Birth-song to Heauens late-borne King:</l>
                  <l>And in their song his Prayses doe recount,</l>
                  <l>Whose Prayse all songs of Angels doth furmount.</l>
                  <l>There needed but one Angel to impart,</l>
                  <l>Such nwes to any vnbeleeuing heart.</l>
                  <l>Good newes doth spread it selfe, flies vnrestrain'd,</l>
                  <l>And wished tydings soone are entertain'd.</l>
                  <l>How quickly did this heauenly Sermon sound,</l>
                  <l>Throughout the world? How many hath it found</l>
                  <l>To entertaine it with such constancie,</l>
                  <l>That all Hels rage could not them terrifie?</l>
                  <l>This long expected newes desir'd so much,</l>
                  <l>And by so many, when it came was such,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As that one Angel was enough to bring it,</l>
                  <l>But all the Angels few enough to sing it.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2263:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> The Starre conducting the Wise-men.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOV Which seeke Christ remoue your gazing eyes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uicun{que} <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>istum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eritis, Ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ad alta tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>; Jllic lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> visere son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> perennis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>riae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>udentius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>themer: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iphan.</note>From the dull Earth, advance them to the skies.</l>
                  <l>He who from Heauen did come will not be found,</l>
                  <l>By such as seeke him poaring on the ground:</l>
                  <l>But while their feet doe tread as in disdaine,</l>
                  <l>On Earth, their eyes must fixt on heauen remaine.</l>
                  <l>Euen while he was in bodie here below,</l>
                  <l>No low thing could the way vnto him show:</l>
                  <l>They who so long a iourny to him took</l>
                  <l>Walking on Earth yet still to heauen did look:</l>
                  <l>Who by no Earthly thing conducted are</l>
                  <l>To him on Earth but by an heauenly Starre:</l>
                  <l>A Starre which to the night no seruice lends,</l>
                  <l>Nor on the euer-changing Moone attends.</l>
                  <l>But with the Sunne corriualling in light</l>
                  <l>Shines more by day then other Stars by night.</l>
                  <l>The Poles though in the seas they be not drencht</l>
                  <l>Yet is their luster oft by clowds neere quencht.</l>
                  <l>This Starre still shining through the heauens doth glide,</l>
                  <l>And to that Sunne which neuer sets doth guide;</l>
                  <l>While the Astronomers amazed are</l>
                  <l>Musing which is the Sunne, which is the Starre.</l>
                  <l>But this amazement soone remou'd shall be,</l>
                  <l>When they no more this radiant Starre shall see:</l>
                  <l>Which so long shall before the wisemen runne</l>
                  <l>Till he hath brought them to their far-sought sun,</l>
                  <l>Then no lesse musing shall possesse mens minde</l>
                  <l>That he is vanisht, then that first he shin'de.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:2263:26"/>
                  <l>Still doth a starrre to thee, o Lord, conduct</l>
                  <l>And thy wise-hearted seekers doth instruct</l>
                  <l>Thee so to seeke as that they shall not misse</l>
                  <l>To finde thee, and with thee eternall blisse.</l>
                  <l>A Starre, which though his Orbe be Earth, and here</l>
                  <l>Doth to thy seekers for a time appeare,</l>
                  <l>Yet doth from heauen deriue his splendant light</l>
                  <l>And vnto heauen his followers lead aright.</l>
                  <l>A Starre which doth the Sunne excell so farre</l>
                  <l>As doth the Sunne the smallest twinkling Starre.</l>
                  <l>That Starre the while it did in heauen abide</l>
                  <l>A few (but three) to thee on Earth did guide:</l>
                  <l>This Starre, although it shineth here below</l>
                  <l>Yet Millions vnto heauen the way doth show:</l>
                  <l>And as that Starre appeared not againe</l>
                  <l>When it had brought thē where thou didst remaine,</l>
                  <l>No more shall this, whose office then is done,</l>
                  <l>When once they haue attaind vnto the Sunne;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, let this Starre, thy word, still be my guide,</l>
                  <l>And let my foote-steps neuer from it slide,</l>
                  <l>Vntill it shall me to that Citty bring</l>
                  <l>(The glorious Court of our more glorious King)</l>
                  <l>Where needs nor Sun nor Moone their light display,</l>
                  <l>God and the <hi>Lamb</hi> giues it Eternall Day.<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>In this lifes darknesse we doe need this light:</l>
                  <l>For here we walke by Faith, and not by sight;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But when we come to that celestiall Cittie</l>
                  <l>Then shall we take vp that most joyfull Dittie,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As we haue heard so now, ô Lord, we see</l>
                  <l>How thou in heauen doest walke and we with thee.<note place="margin">Psal. 48.8.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:2263:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 21.2.3.</note>The Wisemen conducted by a starre, and bringing their Presents.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FOLLOW your guide, you wise men of the <hi>East,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Though last invited to this heauenly <hi>Feast.</hi>)</l>
                  <l>The new created Starre, which shewes the way</l>
                  <l>Vnto the blessed Babe, and will not stay</l>
                  <l>Till he hath brought you where he doth abide,</l>
                  <l>But shortly after out of sight will slide:</l>
                  <l>For when the Sunne with beames the World once graces,</l>
                  <l>The Stars ashamed are to shew their faces.</l>
                  <l>Think not that you are gul'd so farre to come,</l>
                  <l>To seeke a King, and find so base a roome:</l>
                  <l>Thinke not that roome is base where there is seene,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Starre without, a glorious Sunne within.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here shall you find the Child you farre haue sought,</l>
                  <l>Present to him the Presents you haue brought:</l>
                  <l>Giue <hi>Gold</hi> to him as <hi>Tribute</hi> to your King,</l>
                  <l>As God,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hus, Myrrhā Regi{que} homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i{que} Deo{que} Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a ferunt. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>encus Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iter. Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Da Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ym. non semel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>audatus.</note> for seruice, <hi>Incence</hi> to him bring:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bring <hi>Myrrhe</hi> t' embalme the Man who once must die,</l>
                  <l>Least all mankind doe die eternally.</l>
               </lg>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WALKE on you Wisemen stay not till yee come</l>
                     <l>Where wisdome hath tane vp an homely roome:</l>
                     <l>Thinke not so long a journie little worth,</l>
                     <l>Wiser you shall returne then yee came forth:</l>
                     <l>Will you be wise indeed? Drinke of this Well,</l>
                     <l>Which Wisdome opens in a silly Cell:</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2263:27"/>
                     <l>Drinke of this Well your thirst to satisfie,</l>
                     <l>But ere you Drinke vse th' <hi>Addars</hi> policie.</l>
                     <l>Your humane Wisdome Poyson first eject,</l>
                     <l>So shall you find true Wisdomes sweete effect:</l>
                     <l>Had you come fooles, you wiser should become,</l>
                     <l>Then all the Wisards you haue left at home.</l>
                     <l>Returne, and being return'd report and say</l>
                     <l>To those Star-gazers that at home did stay.</l>
                     <l>Not all the Stars they euer saw could shew,</l>
                     <l>So much to them as one Starre did to you.</l>
                     <l>Tell them, in all the Heauens they neuer shall</l>
                     <l>A greater find, then you found in a Stall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O thou eternall Wisdome make me wise,</l>
                     <l>That from my Heathen-country I may rise:</l>
                     <l>My Fathers house and Kindred to forsake</l>
                     <l>Cause me, that I to thee my way may take:</l>
                     <l>And that I may not erre nor goe astray,</l>
                     <l>Let that bright Starre, thy Word, lead me the way.</l>
                     <l>Be that vnto my feet a light, and to</l>
                     <l>My steps a safe-conducting Lamp, that so</l>
                     <l>With these Wisemen I safely may attaine</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Place, where thou, Lord, doest remaine.</l>
                     <l>And finding thee who art my soules rich store,</l>
                     <l>Let me fall downe and humbly thee adore;</l>
                     <l>Offring those guifts which cannot offred be</l>
                     <l>By me, vnlesse I them receiue from thee.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Gold</hi> of true <hi>Obedience</hi> I will bring,</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Tribute</hi> due to mine eternall King.</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Frankinsence</hi> shall be my daily <hi>Prayers,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(A pleasing Perfume vnto thee) <hi>My Teares</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shed for thy Death, and for my sinne, shall be</l>
                     <l>My mourning <hi>Myrrhe</hi> still dropping vnto thee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2263:28"/>
                     <l>O let this <hi>Myrrhe</hi> still drop, till I arriue,</l>
                     <l>Where thou and thine in lasting joyes doe liue,</l>
                     <l>Where thou, from whom all comfort doth arise,</l>
                     <l>Wipest all teares from true repentant eyes:</l>
                     <l>Where they shall reape in Ioy who here below,</l>
                     <l>The pretious seed of plenteous teares do sowe:</l>
                     <l>Sorrow (thou sayest) may for a night remaine,</l>
                     <l>But in the morning Ioy returnes againe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All this lifes Night I'le be content with sorrow,</l>
                     <l>That night once past, Ioy may giue me <hi>goodmorrow.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> The Infant sought by <hi>Herod</hi> to be destroyed.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IS this into the World thy welcome, <hi>Lord?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is this the entertainement men afford</l>
                  <l>To thee, who com'st from heauen to blisse the earth,</l>
                  <l>To handsell with thy blood thy blessed Birth?</l>
                  <l>No sooner Borne then forthwith sought to die,</l>
                  <l>Enforc'd ere thou can'st goe, or creepe, to flie!</l>
                  <l>Will they assoone as thou to Earth art come,</l>
                  <l>Needs send thee back vnto thy Heauenly home?</l>
                  <l>And must the Butcher and the Midwife striue,</l>
                  <l>He how to kill, She how to keepe aliue?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod,</hi> what hast? Adjourne thy crueltie,</l>
                  <l>He had not come but that he meant to die;</l>
                  <l>But not so soone as to the World he's showne,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet at mans appointment, but his owne.</l>
                  <l>Think'st thou to haue his life at thy command,</l>
                  <l>Who hath both thine and all mens in his hand?</l>
                  <l>What King or Creature else can him depriue</l>
                  <l>Of life, by whom all Kings, all Creatures liue?</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:2263:28"/>
                  <l>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Iohn. 10 17.18.</note>The Power of his owne life he doth retaine</l>
                  <l>To lay it downe and take it vp againe.</l>
                  <l>None takes it from him till it be his minde,</l>
                  <l>And then tis not tane from him, but resign'd.</l>
                  <l>But first much heauenly Doctrine must be taught,</l>
                  <l>And to confirme it weighty wonders wrought.</l>
                  <l>The dead must first be vnto life restor'd,</l>
                  <l>To shew that he of life and death is Lord:</l>
                  <l>Of all his Enemies malignant crew</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>Death is the last he meaneth to subdue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>Herod</hi> who so soone would him destroy</l>
                  <l>More hastie is then any <hi>Butchers</hi> boy.</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Butcher</hi> is so fell but will allow</l>
                  <l>The new falne <hi>Lambe</hi> some little time to grow:</l>
                  <l>For well he knowes it is not fit for food</l>
                  <l>While yet the milk is hardlie turn'd to blood.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Lamb</hi> is sought to render vp his life,</l>
                  <l>While yet his throat is lesser then the knife.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O <hi>Lambs</hi> an harmelesse, yet an haplesse Creature,</l>
                  <l>Who haue so many Enemies in nature,</l>
                  <l>So many that doe seeke on you to prey,</l>
                  <l>And think you wrong them by a small delay!</l>
                  <l>While the poore <hi>Ewe</hi> is yet her <hi>Lamb-kin</hi> licking</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Rauen</hi> thinks it long ere he be picking.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tis still thy lot, ô Lord: No sooner brought</l>
                  <l>To Birth art thou but straight thy death is sought.</l>
                  <l>No sooner now in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> thou borne art</l>
                  <l>(The house of bread, the true beleeuers heart)</l>
                  <l>But Hells feirce <hi>Herod</hi> and his cursed Court</l>
                  <l>Sore vext, and sore perplext at the report,</l>
                  <l>Doe seeke thine infant-life away to take,</l>
                  <l>Whose very name makes King and kingdome quake</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2263:29"/>
                  <l>No maruell if he seeke to take away</l>
                  <l>Thy life, who comst to saue whom he would slay,</l>
                  <l>And knowes his Kingdome soone will be dejected</l>
                  <l>When once thy righteous scepter is erected.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In spite of Hell and Hellish <hi>Herod</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>And maugre all their spite and spleene can doe,</l>
                  <l>O let my soule a litle <hi>Bethlehem</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>An house of bread and be thou borne in me,</l>
                  <l>Thou who from heauen didst bring the bread of life:</l>
                  <l>Ile neuer dread the cruell <hi>Tirants</hi> knife:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Christ once in Christians borne is neuer slaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And saueth them in whom he doth remaine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rage Hell, rage <hi>Herod</hi> and with enuie burst,</l>
                  <l>Let all th' Infernall Furies doe their worst:</l>
                  <l>Thou, who an Infant, saud'st thy selfe by flying</l>
                  <l>Shalt by abiding saue my soule from dying,</l>
                  <l>How can I perish? life doth me preserue.</l>
                  <l>I haue the Bread of life: How can I starue?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O let it be my care, Lord, to keepe thee,</l>
                  <l>And then I shall be sure thou wilt keepe me!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> The Infants slaine by <hi>Herod.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>INFANTS prepare your throats, Parents your eyes,</l>
                  <l>Streame you forth teares for they must streāe forth blood:</l>
                  <l>Turne into sobs and sighs your Lullabies,</l>
                  <l>And place the Coffin where the Cradlestood:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If so much favour yet you may obtaine,</l>
                  <l>To burie those you bare but to be slaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The pleasing painfull burthen you did carrie,</l>
                  <l>Some fortie weekes within your weary wombes,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:2263:29"/>
                  <l>Must not with you at most past two yeares tarrie.</l>
                  <l>Behold the irrelenting slayer comes;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who will the name of Mothers you denie,</l>
                  <l>Ere the poore Infant yet can Mamma crie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Weepe <hi>Rachel,</hi> weepe, and let thy teares abound</l>
                  <l>Aboue the rest, because thy losse is double,<note place="margin">
                        <p>
                           <hi>It is prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> That</hi> Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <hi>lost more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren then because th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Text spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> of hers in plurall.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Locum mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis ictibus interempto inuenit Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> plaga des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> dat patens gulo{que} mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> pugio est. Prudentiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Cathemer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> hymo. Epip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </p>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>More vnder two yeares old with thee are found:</l>
                  <l>Thy ofter teeming breeds thee greater trouble.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus only for the slaughter to giue life,</l>
                  <l>To haue beene fertile only for the knife.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Base Butchers who so prompt and readie are</l>
                  <l>To execute the cursed Tyrants will,</l>
                  <l>What instruments of Death will yee prepare</l>
                  <l>Wherewith these <hi>Lambs</hi> that liu'd but now, to kill?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Scarse can you find a Knife so little, but</l>
                  <l>Tis greater then the Throats you come to cut.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pen-knifes the fittest tooles are yee can take,</l>
                  <l>For of those members you meane to destroy,</l>
                  <l>Their Saviour meanes so many Pens to make;</l>
                  <l>Wherewith their Names (ere some doe names enjoy)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shall in his booke of Life be registred,</l>
                  <l>With their owne blood, which for his sake was shed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Tygers into humane shape transchang'd,</l>
                  <l>With more then Tygers thirst of blood possest!</l>
                  <l>Could men from manhood be so farre estrang'd,</l>
                  <l>To snatch the suckling from the Mothers brest,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And in her sight the Cradle-swathes defile</l>
                  <l>With that new blood which was but milke ere while?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Peace, prettie Innocents, forbeare to crie,</l>
                  <l>Receiue with willing sides the fatall blow,</l>
                  <l>Best is that Death which comes in Infancie,</l>
                  <l>The longer life is but prolonged woe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2263:30"/>
                  <l>Who Yesterday was borne and dies to day,</l>
                  <l>Comes to his Port as soone as sets to sea.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your journies end at setting forth you met,</l>
                  <l>Your whole dayes taske you in the morning finisht:</l>
                  <l>Your Sun no sooner did arise, but set,</l>
                  <l>Yet was your day encreast, your night diminisht.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You op'd your eyes, and seeing nought but paine,</l>
                  <l>In this base World, you clos'd them vp againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Death, to be priz'd 'boue any lifes best rate,</l>
                  <l>Saue that best life which doth such Death ensue!</l>
                  <l>Your Saviours kindnesse you anticipate,</l>
                  <l>Dying for him, ere he doe die for you:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How soone are you of Martyrs Crownes possessors,</l>
                  <l>Who Martyrs were ere you could be confessors?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rachel,</hi> although thy cause of greife be great;</l>
                  <l>Yet to be comforted refuse no more</l>
                  <l>As if thy Children were not; They are yet:</l>
                  <l>And thou and they more happie then before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou, who by bearing Martyrs get'st renowne,</l>
                  <l>They, who exchange a Cradle for a Crowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why sai'st thou then, they are not? Say thou rather,</l>
                  <l>Thy Children neuer truely were till now:</l>
                  <l>They 're not with thee, they're with their heauenly Father:</l>
                  <l>They are aboue, they are not here below,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why should'st thou then for them make such complaints,</l>
                  <l>Who neuer were but Innocents and Saints?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O blessed <hi>Babes</hi> who from your <hi>Mothers wombe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Abrahams</hi> bosome fetch a speedy spring</l>
                  <l>Ere you can goe. Who ere you speak; are come</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>Halleluiiahs</hi> vnto him to sing:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who did vnto your Parents only shew you</l>
                  <l>But on his Sonne as rarest Iewels bestow you!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:2263:30"/>
                  <l>He, least you long with sinners should abide,</l>
                  <l>From among Men you to himselfe doth take,</l>
                  <l>Of your short swathing cloathes which red were dy'de</l>
                  <l>With your owne bloud he long white Roabes doth make;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dy'de in his owne which only hath this might,</l>
                  <l>To die the deepest scarlet into white.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O from how many blowes doth one blow free you!</l>
                  <l>How pure are they whom bloud doth thus Baptize?</l>
                  <l>Nere shal your parents hence forth weeping see you:</l>
                  <l>These Teares doe wipe all others from your eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With Palmes in hands victorious ore your foes</l>
                  <l>Follow you doe the <hi>Lamb</hi> where ere he goes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why had not I of that blest Beauie beene</l>
                  <l>Who from the shell so soone to Heauen did flee?<note place="margin">Death the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect and so Daughter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> sinne.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ripe for saluation sooner then for sinne,</l>
                  <l>Whom few small wounds from many great did free:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To whom an <hi>Antidote</hi> the <hi>Daughter</hi> lent,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Mothers</hi> poysoned <hi>Potions</hi> to preuent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Blinde superstition! did no Day appeare</l>
                  <l>On which thine inauspitious Crosse might rest</l>
                  <l>To stampe it for vnluckie all the yeare</l>
                  <l>But only this which made so many blest?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why should that day to vs disastrous be,</l>
                  <l>Which them from all disasters did set free?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If sins soule-clogging shackles off to shake,</l>
                  <l>If nere to doe nor speak nor think amisse,</l>
                  <l>If all t'enioy that man can happie make,</l>
                  <l>If that a Crosse day be that brings all this,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then all my Dayes that Day awayt will I,</l>
                  <l>To Crosse and cancell all my miserie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>